He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48.
Verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
in our time.
year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick, and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God and explain.
by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers,
dragon slayers, behemoth basher's,
Leviathan Laszlers.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
And I assume that my co-host,
Father Stephen D'Young, is with me from Lafayette Louisiana.
Where else would I be?
Okay, just, I mean,
I don't know, you could be phoning it in,
literally, phoning it in.
I had to do that in some of the early episodes,
if you recall.
I do recall.
I could play some clips.
Yeah.
I'm Father Edustivan Daiming.
I'm in a Mayas, Pennsylvania.
And we are live.
So if you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346.
And you can talk to us.
And we're going to get your calls in second half of the show
and our very own, most beloved,
and much as good true to you, will be taking your calls.
This episode is sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute
at St. Constance Heat College, which
exists to advance the study and application of ortho-
Christianity in faithfulness to holy tradition. OSI is offering online courses this fall,
including a five-week course on the Book of Enoch taught by you, Father Stephen Dian.
You can learn about the courses. That's the rest of you.
You better, yeah. Everyone, it's a while. I know they better sign up soon. You can learn
Learn about the courses registered at orthodoxstudies.com.
last LOS and if you register using that link, you'll get a free copy of Father Stevens'
ebook Apocrypha from Ancient Faith Publishing and registration is now open.
A bunch of people have already signed up, so this is pretty good.
Unlike how you normally download my books, this time you won't have to feel guilty.
All those bootleg PDFs you guys got out there.
Yeah, so it's been a hot minute since we did a brain bending episode, I think.
So.
If that's what you came for, Fair listener, tonight you are in for a treat.
If not, good night.
Anyway, we're talking tonight about time, which if anyone is keeping scores on my side,
yes it is.
Now, what even is-
Now, everyone is going to think we're doing another Azazel episode because you did that.
But what is it?
Is time a thing?
Does God experience time?
Is time just an illusion for humans?
and Father Stephen Wise at the just yesterday.
All my troubles seem so far away
And things were going so well with the Rolling Stones and you had to sell you with the Beatles
Spiciest take of all time rolling stuff better than the Beatles. I did recently. I did recently watch
Some of the musical watch and listen to some of the musical not on purpose
Some of the musical styleings of Yoko Ohno
So do with that what you will
Were you watching
What's her face's video about the Beatles breaking up? No, no
This was something I ran across on the the Facebooks, but you know, I figure it was a good way for me to start to get into the horror genre
Yeah, well no this this video is defending Yoko. Oh, oh, oh, she did not in fact break up the Beatles. Wow
Wow. Lots of spicy beetles takes going around right?
Indeed. I think one of my favorites.
moments in my life that had to do with the Beatles is there was one time and I'm not joking
about this. I'm still kind of flabbergasted by having had this experience that I walked
into a Catholic bookstore. I can't remember what it is that was playing to by there, but I
walked into a Catholic bookstore and they were playing. It was clearly like some choir singing
Let it be like it was this all female choir singing let it
I was like, what is happening?
Where, where even am I?
I guess that's it.
That means it was in the last 40 years
during which boomers have run the world.
Is what that means.
It's been assimilated to be a Roman Catholic song now.
So that's where we are.
Where are we?
When are we?
So yeah, so before we start our topic proper,
I have something I wanna say.
Uh-oh.
little grandstands
on the part of others even.
I never do that.
I never get out of soapbox or go off on a rant.
But this occurred to me.
It doesn't necessarily fit with the episode.
So, you know, but I don't care.
I have a bully pulpit now, which consists of a microphone I talk into in a room.
Yeah.
So, those people freaking out about this whole Olympics thing.
And, uh,
It's as if they've suddenly discovered that the Olympics are pagan.
What?
And if you're one of those folks who just discovered this, I have bad news for you
because the Olympics have always been pagan.
They started out pagan.
The, we talked about in our episodes, we were talking about werewolfism,
Like the first one a guy sacrificed a baby, a committed an act of cannibalism.
to get demonic power to win the Olympics.
Okay.
The Olympics are pagan.
Why am I pointing this out?
Not just to say like, yeah, duh.
Why do you think the opening ceremonies look like that?
But I think this is emblematic of a larger thing,
a larger cultural thing that, well, it's not germane to the
night's topic is very germane to the theme of our show as a whole.
And that's that we've been sold this bill of goods since we were kids in our education.
We've been taught about this thing that isn't real, and it's called Western civilization,
where they try to draw a historical through line, starting in like ancient Sumer,
and ending depending on your vintage either in like
19th century Germany or 19th century British Empire or if you're more my age ending in
late 20th century United States of America. And this is the March of Civilization.
This is all one thing, one stream. And religiously, what this does is it tries to draw
through line from Sumerian religion.
a development aligned from there to 19th century German Lutheranism, the 19th
century Church of England or 20th century, late 20th century American evangelicalism
as the culmination not just of Christianity but of human religion as a whole
finally got it right but everything along the way is part of this tapestry, part of
this one tradition. Right? We all grew up thinking that cupids were cherubs.
They're not.
And so when this whole idea was concocted through the renaissance and the Enlightenment,
when the basically European pagan tradition was fusing itself to the Western Christian
tradition, it was sort of a devil's bargain from both sides.
There were people who didn't...
like the Western Christian tradition and were chafing at it because they wanted to live their
lives or exercise their intellects in other ways and so they wanted the freedom that a revised and
hollowed out version of the Western pagan tradition offered them and then on the other side
there were people who were still loyal to the Western Christian tradition but who wanted to claim
credit for the glories of Greece and Rome and all the pagan stuff at Pagan Art.
and culture. And so they came to this agreement, we'll just fuse all this together and call it
Western culture or Western civilization. And now, very timely, you could go all over YouTube.
You know, it's in some of our own circles, so shall we say, and five people talking about the
demise of the West and the demise of Western civilization and Western culture. This thing that was
phony and never existed, that we were all pretending to exist. It's not that this thing was real and
And now it's...
going away. It's that those two things which are fundamentally incompatible, Christianity and
paganism, are pulling themselves apart again. And guess what? The paganism side is rediscovering
its antipathy toward Christianity faster than the opposite is happening. Because the folks who are
or still on the western Christian side, still want to keep things like the Olympics.
Still want to keep a bunch of these things that ultimately are not germane to the Christian
tradition that come out of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment and the pagan-elt recovery
they're in.
They want to cling to those.
They want to keep those.
Right?
And just keep pretending that they're Christian.
But the pagan side won't accept that bargain anymore.
They're feeling their oats now.
Right?
And they want to take the back and just be pagan as pagan as they could be.
Now that's going to lead to them to very dark places.
Hopefully some of them will yo yo back to Christianity and realize what they've lost.
But that's what's happening in our culture right now.
That's what everybody could observe the opening ceremony of the Olympics was, oh,
the Olympics are now just being openly pagan again.
They're not pretending anymore.
But will they bring back the poetry?
contest. I'm just saying I'm not saying that won't be pagan.
Oh, if it's pagan poetry. Yeah. I mean, there's some good
pagan poetry. The Iliad. That's the attitude. See, see, you're
trying to, you tried to. So yeah, so that's we just need to
acknowledge that that was always a fiction. That was always a
fiction. Right? The the the the
The transcription of the...
scriptures, your worship Christianity, corrects all of those teachings of the nations. The nations worshiped demons, not God.
True story. Both the Torah and St. Paul say so.
And we need to stop trying to fuse the city of God and city of man and trying to hold those things together and pretend that the same city.
Oh, first Santa Gustin reference because they hate these coming back tonight
I know. I know. I know. I'm I'm warming up. So end of rant. All right.
Very germane to our show in general. Not necessarily to our topic tonight.
But hey, are we being relevant? Are we up to the minute? Are we? Yes.
I was watching, but I'm watching all these takes. And it's just like,
hey, you got to get your takes in. Why did you assume that the opening ceremonies for the
Olympic Games would be in any way, Christian?
More outrage needed.
Why?
Anyway.
Yeah.
It's paganism.
And the parts that I know there are people out there
going, well, no, but since they brought it back
it's about other things.
One of those other things it's about,
the brotherhood of man,
liberty, equality, and fraternity,
enlightenment, values.
That's not Christian either.
Yeah.
That's grounded.
in a repudiation of Christianity too.
Like, that's not there was no Christian element.
For people go watch Cheriots of fire at one multiple Oscars.
And it has clips from Gilbert and Sullivan productions.
Yes.
So media literacy.
Media literacy.
It's the first time I've ever heard bits from HMS Pinafore,
which is a much, a much on
underrated production in my humble opinion.
Yes.
Especially the Pirates of Pinsance.
The very loves Pirates of Pinsance.
The most popularized kids version.
That's right.
There's a lot to love about Pirates of Pinsance.
I grant you that, especially having recently been rather close to Pinsance.
I did not see any pirates, but HMS Pinter 4.
Mekado.
I mean, there's a lot of good Gilbert and Sullivan people.
I'm just letting you know.
On that, we can agree.
All right.
It's the A-Word-Zai-Bai-Tai
Let's talk. Yes. I thought time was on my side, but no, it's not. No. Yeah, so we are
tonight talking about time. And so yes, as father Andrew alluded to before my
diet tribe. This is this is this is good you know we have we've had a few that are
a little bit chewed.
this one's crunchy. Yeah, supposed to
crunchy like chewy like you know they're
a little gummy like you got you a steak
right you got a you got chew on it a
while before you try swallow it. So that's
a that's a fair warning but we're going to
try not to rush through it and we're going
to be developing the things we talk about
night tonight some more in our next episode
which is just next week.
Let's check.
We have a little bit of a weird schedule this month mainly because of travel. So we're having an episode tonight
August 1st. We're having another one next week, August 8th, and then you have to wait three weeks
August 29th
So yes
We just want to keep people guessing yeah, yeah
But yes tonight and then we're gonna pick up on some of these same themes next week and
Even though this is deep stuff. I think it's important stuff
And I don't think it's these
important like framing, these are important framing issues, which if you don't deal with them,
you can have all kinds of whacked out theology as a result.
You know, like Calvinism.
Yeah.
Right.
And a lot of that comes from something we've talked about a lot of the show, which is,
right, we're humans.
So we speak about everything from a human perspective.
And there is always the danger.
Because we always, all humans would re-communicate with each other. We're always all speaking from the human perspective.
For us to get confused and think that our perspective is objective reality.
And that's especially dangerous when it comes to talking about God.
And pretending that my subjective perspective about God is the reality of God, as if I could comprehend that.
and...
So that's really where we're going to start.
We're going to start tonight with talking about how God relates to time.
And so far as this is a thing we could even talk about.
Yeah.
So you're going to hear a lot of knots.
We'll be apophatic for like three hours straight you guys.
Yeah. Well, not entirely.
Not for about.
Well, enough for three hours.
I'm exempt.
For a good hour and a half out of the three.
But yeah, so we're going to start that direction.
But, and so a lot of this is going to be, we've got to blow up some common misconceptions
of what that relationship might be.
All of which are like I just said, really based around taking sort of the human perspective
and human experience of time and trying to then generalize that onto God and make it sort
of objective and absolute, and applied to him the same way it applies to us, which of course.
we know better than that, right?
But so to help us get a window into this, right?
So they're diving straight into the way God and time are related.
We're going to start with the way God and space are related.
Because this I think is a little clearer, a little at least,
or a little easier to understand.
And then once we've sort of clarified and talked
and talked about the relation.
between God and space, right, then we can kind of move from there by way of
analogy to talk about God and time. Okay. I'm track. So when we think about God
and space, right, we're talking about space, not like the final frontier, right?
This is spaces in just extension in space, right?
Distance, places, right?
Uh
We will talk about God acting in a place, meaning, you know, God heals someone.
Okay, God heals someone.
That person is healed at a particular time and in a particular place.
Okay, right.
So when that person is healed, it's not, oh, suddenly time has been rewritten and they were never sick, right?
but
The healing happens at a particular time and it happens at a particular place.
The place where that person is who is healed, right?
But, right, so we could say God healed that person on this day at this hospital.
But what we don't mean by that is that like God physically traveled to that hospital and healed
that person. Yeah, or as as one person once put it.
What does God need with a starship?
Yes.
He doesn't need to travel there.
That's right.
So God doesn't need to like cross space from one point to another, right?
Go from here to there.
Right?
Where God, you know, he's doing one thing.
You know, in in one place, you know, stopping someone from crossing the street, right?
When they would have gotten hit by a car and then now he has to get across town to go heal somebody at the hospital.
Like...
Superman. We all understand that's ridiculous right when we're talking about God right yeah yeah
So it's not that God is insupply right like God is not in some particular place and from that
Place he is sort of doing all the things he's doing everywhere else
Right
Is not mission control right
So we under we understand this with space, but the effects right the effects of what God does
right? Those are localized in a particular place and a particular time, right?
Because the recipients, the created recipients of what God does, the person being
healed, the grass that is growing, right? The person who is finding repentance and
salvation, their created things and they are exist at a particular point in
in space and in time. Right? It's all there.
effects of what God does are there in the created world, but God Himself is not sort of localized
in that particular place in order to do that where he able to have to move around.
And this gets into, of course, what's usually referred to as God's omnipresence.
everywhere. But there are kind of bad ways we think about this.
two. Because we say, okay, God's omnipresent God's everywhere. But we don't mean that
just like God is really big and spread out through the whole universe. Right. Right.
That's not what we mean. Right. Because we don't believe that God like occupies space
right in the way that created things do right?
But that's...
not a good way to think about what we mean by God's omnipresence.
And we get some help from this from now Saint Dmitry Estantiloy of Romania, who is Orthodox
dogmatics, taught us that God's attributes are super essential.
What does that mean?
Not to be confused with super essential.
Yes.
new Pra which means
above and beyond effectively. Right. Right. So when we, the word essential comes from
essay, right, being, right, a being, uh, from the Latin. And what we mean by that is, right,
everything we know that's created is a thing. They're created things, right? So me, Father
Steve A. D. Young is a thing.
A chair is a thing.
Right.
a bottle cap is a thing, right? These are things, right? And all of those things,
have an essence, all of those things have attributes, right, that we can describe about them,
right? But so when we say that God is super essential, we're saying God is not a thing.
He's not a thing like created things.
So God is not just a really big thing, not a really...
big human, not a really big angel, not a really big object, right?
God is not a thing in the sense that created things are things, right?
We talked about this in an earlier episode where we pointed out that we don't
believe God exists.
In the sense that what I mean, when I say this chair exists or I exist or a pen
exists or a bottle capping.
exists is not the same thing that it means for God to exist.
Because God is not a created thing.
Right.
So it means something fundamentally different.
And so what does that mean when we think about God's omnipresence?
Right.
Well, that means God is not just like a very big thing.
Who spread out all over.
God is not traveling around.
Right.
God is not a thing.
So what that means ultimately is
that it is equally true to say that God is everywhere in the sense that there is no
there is nowhere in creation there is no place in creation where God is not.
This is what we're saying about negative statements. There's no place that God is not.
And so in that sense he is everywhere. But it is equally true to say that God is nowhere in the
sense that
He cannot be restricted to any particular place.
Like, oh, God is right here, as opposed to anywhere else.
Right. Right. He's here and not there.
And some of you may be thinking, well, what about like the tabernacle or the temple?
Right. We're the place where the presence of God was.
Well, read in the Old Testament, read in the Hebrew Scriptures, what God keeps saying.
saying every time he-
talks about, especially the temple. He's constantly saying he does not dwell in houses made by human hands.
Right? He is not a thing. Right? And so yes, while he is present there, that doesn't mean he isn't present everywhere else.
Right? And God reinforced that over and over again because having the tabernacle or the temple is the place where humans go.
to encounter God, right? Could potentially confuse us humans into thinking that, oh God is there as opposed to other places.
Yeah. Right. So this is kind of giving us a picture of how God relates to space, right?
Simply put, spatial categories, like here, there, far, near.
They don't apply literally to-
like we could talk about feeling far away from God or feeling close to God, but we all understand that's an analogy.
Right, we don't literally mean like, well, I feel closer to God now, like five meters closer. Right, like you'd look at someone like they were insane.
If they said that, right. Right. Right. Like, did you measure?
What? Right? That's not a literal question of space. Okay. So time...
Even though we experience it differently, and we're going to get there, we're going to
talk about the way humans experience time.
That's where we're heading.
But time is very much like space in this regard.
And so having talked about how God relates to space, that can now help us a little bit
in terms of starting to think about how God relates to time.
So going back to...
an example we already used. God heals a person. That person is in a particular place and so that
healing takes place in that place. That is the place where it happens. It also happens in a
particular time, as we said. The person experiences that healing at that time in that place.
Okay, but that doesn't mean that God acts in a particular way.
time. What do we mean by that? Well, sort of the same thing we meant by place,
where we said, well, he doesn't travel around to do this thing over there, and then
this other thing over here. Same thing is true in time. God doesn't have like a
checklist every day. Right? Like, okay, you know, here's a list of the 150,000
infants who are going to be conceived today and the time of conception so I can
create their souls, right, like in order and...
Here's all the new mushrooms that are growing and here's all the healings
I'm gonna write God doesn't have like a big list of things and he like goes through them in order over the course of a day
Right obviously
Nobody actually thinks that literally right
Maybe William Lane crank but no one's serious thinks that literally I mean
This is this is the image of God is Santa Claus, right making a list checking it twice
All these things you gotta take care of.
Yeah, yeah, that he's sort of doing
Micro-managing the universe right by doing all these and doing them all in order because he experiences time the way we do, right?
It's easy to start thinking that way because what are we doing when we think that way?
Well, that's how my life is I have a bunch of things I have to do today
At places I need to be at certain times and so I go through and I try to check those off and get everything done and everything take
get care of, right? But I'm a human.
God is not like me. In that way, I am a created thing. My dogs have things they need to do each day,
like lay around and get into trouble and eat and go to the bathroom and they check those off one
at a time. But God is not a created thing who needs to do that. So we understand that. We just
understand that God does it. It isn't that God does something
at five o'clock on a Friday, it's that a person is healed
at five o'clock on a Friday and God did it.
Right?
Yep.
That may seem like it, but that's an important distinction.
Right?
Because one of those has God existing like in time.
Yeah, I don't think we can underline too much
that God is not bound by anything at all.
Like there is this is
This is one of the roots of a lot of heresies,
is this notion that God has to obey rules,
or God is bound by something.
And we've talked about some of this before,
but this is really, really fleshing out
the time aspect of it, this time around.
Right.
God doesn't experience a succession of moments.
Yeah.
Right, like there's this moment,
and then the next moment, the next moment,
we experience that.
God doesn't.
And
And part of that is, and we're going to talk about this more in a minute.
We'll tell more to do it.
But God doesn't experience anything.
But we'll come back to that.
Yeah, just hold on to that idea.
Everybody.
So that idea, though, right?
Once we really understand that God doesn't do something at a certain time,
but God does something.
and those of us who live in time experienced
it at a certain time. Right. God is not in a parallel world. Right. There's not a time zone in heaven.
Right. It is not 6.32 p.m. in heaven right now, or 7.32 or 5.32.
Wherever you think heaven is. I mean, West Virginia is almost there. Right. But
But that's what they say.
It's not like an hour off, right?
Um.
Right, so there's not like this parallel heaven timeline that God is living in, right?
And once you really understand that, all kinds of theology falls apart.
In our second half, we're going to get into some of the biblical words and biblical concepts
related to this.
But this kind of dismantles Calvinism.
Sorry, not sorry, Calvinists.
the sense that
If God is outside of time and space, which he has to be to be God, right, let me be clear.
If he's not, he's a creature.
He's just a big creature.
Yeah, there's something bigger than God than worship that.
Yes, right.
But there's not, right?
So God is outside of time and space, right?
And if that's true, then it's impossible for God to make decrees or plans or choices
or decisions before something happens in the created world. Like that language
doesn't make sense, right? And I know what some of our Calvinist friends are
thinking right now. They're thinking to themselves self. We talk about the
logical order of the decrees, not the temporal order that doesn't get you out
of this.
Because that implies God has to do things in some kind of logical order.
Right?
So the idea that God is somehow submitted to the laws of logic.
So then isn't the logos the actual God and not the God you're calling God
if he's bound by yet.
That dog don't hunt.
Yes, this applies to you too, William Lane Craig, who thinks God has to follow the laws of
watching.
Someone in the chat is asking about Molinism.
I can't believe it.
Well, we just, we just mentioned William Lane Craig.
There you go.
Okay.
So, yeah, Molinism makes no sense because there God has knowledge of creatures before,
again before
or the creatures exist, which implies that God exists in this timeline by himself until
a certain point in that timeline when he starts creating other things.
Molinism has that same problem that Calvinism has.
William Lane Craig will tell you that that's because he
doesn't think God is outside of time. God is bound by time. He's gone by the laws of logic.
I don't think he's come out and admitted he's an open theorist yet, but give it some time.
He puts some time. He's practically wrong. I mean, once he realizes there's a heresy, he doesn't
teach I'm sure he'll graft right on to it. So yeah, acumenism is at the pan here.
Will you blade Craig is the pan here?
Wow.
So for those of you who like Bashi Calvittis,
for those of you who like Bashi Calvittis,
will you blade Craig?
You're going to love this show.
But for those who just like Bashi Calvittis,
if you're Armenians out there,
I got bad news for you.
This kind of ruins your party too.
Yeah.
Because it's all dependent on this idea
that God is in some way bound by linear.
time. Right. That God knows things in advance. Right. So God exists at a particular time and then knows
what's going to happen like the next day. Even though it hasn't happened yet for him. See the problem?
Yeah. Right. So that doesn't work either. And of course, open theism doesn't work because
Open the theism requires God to be basically a big creature.
Yep. Yeah, it's almost like a kind of a paganizing of God, you know, he's just, yeah, yeah.
So all that's just kind of mess, right?
So then, okay.
We've talked about why God has to be separate from apart from time.
The time is an aspect of created things, the created order, the created world, right?
So if time is an aspect of that doesn't apply to God, what is it?
Right?
What is it?
And what do I mean by what is it?
Is it in it even?
So we're just talking about created things, right?
So bottle cap thing, chair thing, pen thing, father Stephen D. Young thing, right?
Created thing that exists in the world.
It's time a thing.
It's time a thing that God created.
Right God created time and it had
some kind of existence. Is that a true statement? Or is time something else?
It's time something else. So we've got proposals on this. We've got
proposals on how to look at time. So if we go to our old friend Flato, if you
haven't x.
He's not recognized him from your brain yet.
Plato is going to talk about time in terms of motion.
Right.
I mean, especially if you accept space as a given.
Yeah.
And you're trying to figure out what is time.
Motion seems kind of a pretty obvious place to go.
Yes.
Yeah.
Because what is motion?
Motion is when something crosses a certain amount of space
in a certain amount of time.
That's motion, right?
So for Plato, of course, there are things that are in stasis that do not move.
Stasis is a perfection for Plato, right?
Not moving, never moving.
You may have some listeners out there who aspire to Plato's perfection, but you shouldn't.
You should go out there.
and do things.
I mean, you could try to be completely immobile, but at a cellular level, you're really quite
busy.
Yes.
I know Keith Richards outlived Richard Simmons.
There's an important lesson there.
But still, you should try and get out and move a little.
I remember when Facebook often was attempting to get me to quote unquote, like the page,
Richard Simmons
for Holy Roman Emperor.
And yeah, I just had to mention that.
The time has passed.
OK.
And Keith Richards outlived him back to the Rolling Stones.
So for Plato, right, any motion is
a sign that something isn't being
it's in the realm of becoming.
Becoming.
And so therefore kind of imperfect on.
Imperfect.
moving toward perfection perhaps.
attempting to emulate perfection perhaps.
And so for Plato, the closest you can get to stasis,
without being stasis, right?
They were, you're still moving,
but the closest you can get to stasis while still moving
is basically moving in a very tight circle.
No, right?
And the tighter the circle, the less you're moving.
So circular motion.
for Plato is like a kind of perfection,
because it's approaching stasis.
Think about, and so for him,
he's going to see not just time is cyclical,
but this is the cycle of the seasons,
the cycles of the constellations,
the stars and the heavens.
These all move in these circular patterns.
Right.
And that circular, those circles, especially the tighter the circle the better, that's
an emulation of the sort of perfection of stasis.
So for Plato, the ultimate place to arrive, right?
Plato really, when you actually understand Plato in his context, right, if you really
understand what Plato is saying, you understand that he relates to Greek paganism, basically
the same way that early Buddhism relates to Hinduism.
That's a kind of intellectualizing of an existing religious tradition.
And not just that, but I mean in the details, Plato believes in reincarnation, Plato believes
ultimately you're trying to achieve stasis, which is losing individuality.
very
very similar where you get with, again, intellectualized paganism is intellectualized paganism.
So your goal writes to get out of this cyclical reincarnation, right?
But so from that comes widespread in the pagan world, right?
you could think about the cycles in Hinduism and Buddhism.
Right? The pagan world time is seen as cyclical. Right? And this is true with the seasons and the
constellations, like I mentioned, this is also true, like when you read Plato, this is how we
understand Atlantis. Right? Civilizations rise and fall and rise and fall and rise and fall. Right?
It's just this perpetual cycle. Okay? Of becoming that's trying to get to actually being actual being
is complete stasis.
So if the cosmos reached perfection, it would all stop moving, it would all be condensed
at a single point.
So kind of hoping for the big crunch, I guess.
So another thing, I mentioned in my earlier rant, bills of goods we were sold as children.
I don't know how popular this one is anymore.
Alright.
But for a long time, especially if you got into philosophy of history at all
There was this rap that
paganism viewed time as cyclical like we were just talking about is just an endless cycle
Whereas they would say
the Hebrews
brought us the idea of time as linear
Yeah, I mean I I heard that a bunch of times.
I probably repeated it a few times myself.
You know, the idea that there's a beginning and end
to history time is basically linear,
you know, that this is what the Bible is doing.
It's like from point A to point B.
Yeah.
And there's a problem that comes when you start
like reading the Bible,
which is that we're gonna get into more of this
the second half of the b-
Bible has lots of cycles in it.
Cycles of feasts.
Weakly cycle of the Sabbath. There's lots of these sort of repeating cycles.
And as you read the text in the stories, you see these
patterns repeating over and over and over again
in the scriptures.
And so then you get some more savvy people like, okay well
So maybe that sick
So, the political versus time is an arrow, right?
Maybe that's a little too simplistic, right?
We'll think about time in terms of the universe
as being sort of a corkscrew or a spiral.
So, yes, there's these repetitions,
but it's also moving in one direction.
Right.
As a way of sort of envisioning time like unfolding.
Um, contrary to all that, here's what I'm going to suggest, which we've suggested on the show before, but we're going to delve into it deeper tonight.
Yeah. And that is that time doesn't exist. Lunchtime doubly so.
Yes. All too short.
Um, you know, like kids these days don't even get like the free 15 minute breaks every two hours.
I know. I know.
We're gonna eat out as soon as they get like the half hour unpaid lunch.
that's it. Right now kids need to unionize I'm telling you anyway so so time doesn't
exist since the time isn't a thing. It's not a thing sorry sorry Star Trek fans
chronotone particles right oh yes I know I love how Star Trek just made up some kind of
particle.
Oh, yeah.
To deal with every like fundamental physical physics problem that they were trying to overcome.
I mean, Brontaton particles very popular for time travel.
Tachyon particles.
Tachyon?
Yeah.
Sometimes, you know, the Tartus, you know, I have harmony, right?
It's a little, a little more vague, a little more fantastical, is it, or a little less
pseudo scientific.
Yeah, time isn't a thing that exists.
Right. Time exists at the level of experience. That doesn't mean it doesn't exist at all.
Right. In the sense that you can like disbelieve it and it goes away.
Yeah, it's not an object. It's not an object.
But remember way back in the long ago time when we talked about our friend, the Mantis shrimp.
Oh man, that was like first year I think.
Yeah. Who can see all those colors that we can't see.
that we don't have a name for, that we don't have a-
way of describing because we fundamentally can't experience them, but the
mantis shrimp can. Right? Those colors don't exist for humans. They do exist for
a mantis shrimp. Yeah. Because he's able to experience them. We're not able to
experience them and color only exists in the realm of experience. Color is an
interpretation right it's the way our
the colors we see as humans are based on the way our eyes process certain wavelengths of light
Right, so if there were no humans left on earth or if all humans were blind like in that weird Apple TV show
see with Jason Momoa
If everyone on earth was blind, right
Could not see at all
Right color would not exist all of those wavelengths of light would still exist yeah
But it's no one could
see anything there would be no color. Yeah, it's like to analogize maybe the
difference between sound and music. You know, there's sounds like there's
vibrations, right? The air can vibrate, but music is an experience that someone
is having of a series of vibrations. Right. The sound of a dog whistle does not
exist for humans, it does for dogs. Yeah. That weird song they used to play
outside circle case that drove off teenagers.
that adults couldn't hear.
Right.
I think.
Yes, you don't know about that?
No.
Yes, there's a particular tone
that like kids could hear up until they're like 16.
Are you serious?
Yes.
And then the shape of the inner your changes that people can't hear it anymore.
Wow.
Then I'll drive the dogs insane.
So be careful if you look at up an experiment with it.
Like I played at once at my house.
I couldn't hear anything at all.
Am I dumb?
dogs went crazy.
There's gotta be some kind of bill and Ted joke in here.
Or, yeah, strange things are fun.
And people started using it to prevent loitering.
Oh man.
They play it like outside their business and stuff.
They get kids to go away.
That's like when I was a stage hand,
we used to play Green Day to get
certain kinds of audiences to go away.
Yeah.
So there is such a sound.
But that sound only exists for...
T-date for younger humans and dogs apparently and probably some other animals, but doesn't exist for adult humans. They can't hear it.
So, that same vibration is going out into the air. You could say that vibration exists, but the sound doesn't exist because you can't hear it.
And the sound is the interpretation.
Yeah.
So this is what we mean when we say time doesn't exist.
Not that it's not real.
It's phenomenological, meaning it's within the realm of
experience, in our case of human experience.
It's something we experience.
And that means just like with those sounds,
different kinds of creatures experience
those sounds differently.
And so different creatures experience time differently.
So, goldfish, for example, have like no persistent memory
of anything.
I think that's an urban legend.
it's true. We're going with it. Although I did use to be an aquearest, but I was never
a goldfish keeper. So I can't, you know, right. Meaning they won't have an experience of time.
We'll get more into the experience of time in our in our third half, right? My dogs experience
time differently than I do.
Okay, yeah, unless they go to sleep, they can't tell how long
long I've been gone. I can walk outside and check the mail or I can be gone for
like five or six hours. They react the exact same way when I walk back into the
door. Right? They're dogs. They experience time differently than I do. Right? But to
verify this, in case you don't believe me, humans, like even a single human,
Even you, the listener, have undoubtedly, we talked about this at least once before,
kind of teasing this episode in the past, you have experienced over the course of your life time
differently at different times. There have been periods of your life. Maybe within the last six
months there have been times where times seem to move really slowly and when it seemed to move very
quickly.
where you can look at different time periods of your life,
quit using the word time periods of your life and say,
yeah, that thing seemed to just time to seem to fly by then.
There's other time it seemed to drag on, right?
So objectively, right, quote unquote, objectively,
time would always move at the rate of one second per second.
Right?
That's the speed of time, one second per second.
So
Right, but we all know how variable it is in our experience because it is just a factor of our experience
And this is ultimately why
God doesn't
Isn't
affected by time why time is not a category you can apply to God because God doesn't have experiences
Yeah
Which might sound like a weird thing to say, but think about this for a second boys and girls
And experience means you're being acted upon, right?
And experience changes you in some way.
You're undergoing something, right?
You're being acted upon.
So that means that you are to use a technical philosophical term,
passible, P-A-S-S-I-B-L-E, not passable,
like this tastes passable, but passable,
there was able to be acted upon.
So that's why we have experiences because...
because we're able to be acted upon.
We can be impinged upon.
But God is not, this is a core theological teaching
in Christianity.
God is not passable.
Right.
So I'm not able to be acted upon.
I can experience something I've never experienced before.
I can learn something I didn't know before.
I can see something I haven't seen before.
Right.
All these experiences, I can experience something
I've never experienced before.
That can't happen to God.
Right?
God doesn't learn things or see new things that he hasn't said.
God is God.
Right?
So this whole category of experience, as Father Andrew said, requires being acted upon.
God is not acted upon.
Meaning God doesn't have experiences.
And so categories like time or like distance in space don't apply to him.
Right.
Being acted upon, being passable, having experiences is a quality of being a creature, being created, being finite.
Right? I have added a finite number of experiences in my life, and when I have a new one, I am adding one more, but that's not true of God.
Right? It can't be. If he's God.
So this is why we experienced something like
time. Right. It is an ordering of our other experiences essentially. Right. Now this may
have raised a question for someone. Right. This may raise a question for someone. And
we're going to come back to this in a little more detail. But I'm sure there's someone
out there. You may have already had your ears perk up when I was talking about God not
doing anything in a place or traveling to a place to do something. Some of you guys out
they're maybe thinking what about
Lord Jesus Christ. He traveled places at heal people. Yeah, we actually just had someone in the
someone in the YouTube chat asked, you know, what about Christ? Does he have experiences, right?
Yeah, I weigh ahead of you, pal. Yeah. You're lunch. Anyway. You're tracking Sam. Don't worry,
you're with us. Yeah. Yeah. This is all the notes. Right. And you made me want, well, like,
Like, didn't Christ as out Christ was born as an infant, he grew up, right?
Like...
Didn't he have experiences at experience time? We're gonna come back to this in more detail
But for now we have to say remember once again, right anytime you start thinking about
what
Would it be like to be our Lord Jesus Christ?
What would he like to be the second person of the Trinity made flesh for our salvation?
Like bro again, I can't even understand what's like to be a bat
I'm not figuring that one out, right?
I don't know what it's like to be a bat.
I don't know what it's like to be father Andrew.
I don't know what it's like to be one of my dogs.
I'm not going to be able to figure out how what it's like to be the divine logos.
Right.
That's the question or not.
So, but we'll come back to that.
We'll come back to the human experience of time.
In the third half, we'll come back to the human experience of time when we're talking about what that is and talk about how that relates to
Our Jesus Christ in the incarnation. So we will come back to that in more detail
Before we're done here
And I think the last time we were talking about this back we were talking about the Manish shrimp. We mentioned deep time
Deep time for those who don't know is the idea of
What do you call quote unquote theoretical time where there is no observer?
Right. Right. There's no one experiencing that time.
I remember back when we just had the simple word prehistoric.
Yeah. Well, that's when no one was able to write about it.
Right. But even before people could write about it, they were there experiencing it.
Yeah. Right. Yeah.
What about before and I mean even if you're...
young earth creationist, right? There's a few days before there's humans. Yep.
There's a few days before there's animals, even, to experience time. Okay. So what is an hour
if there's nothing consciously experiencing that hour? Yeah and I mean...
That's the concept of deep time.
Right.
statistical time.
Yeah, like this is not just a sort of a theological or philosophical thing to say, right?
Like, I'm not a physicist, but I've heard physicists say that one...
And you've played one on TV.
Yeah, I've never played one on TV either.
Although I feel like I could do that.
But physicists will say that particles and waves and whatever behave differently when
they're observed versus when they're not observed.
which is it?
Weird, crazy thing to try to wrap your brain around.
That somehow observation makes the physical world behave
differently.
But it's the reality, that's just the truth.
So why shouldn't that be simply true?
If that's what these people who are at the weird,
weird edges of science are saying about this stuff,
that what does it mean that there's time
when there's no conscious creatures to experience it?
But yeah, I also this
I just want to be clear, this deep time thing is not just a question of old earth people.
Right?
Yeah.
It's not just a question of that.
Right?
You've got at least 24 hours where there's a rock with though, like biological life, experiencing
time on it.
Even if you're a really strict, literalist, young earth creationist.
Right, so you've got at least
24 hours of deep time.
Going on minimum.
There, right?
You can say, well, God's there.
But again, we as we said, God has an experience time in a succession of moments like that.
Yeah.
Right.
We also for the record don't know how angels experience time.
Let's again.
Right.
Because for example, they're not mutable the way we are.
Don't change.
Right.
I mean, it's this is...
assumption that gives rise to different there.
What is frankly one of the most frequent questions we get,
which is why can't angels repent?
This has a lot to do with it.
Yes.
Yes, they are created, they are finite.
Right, so I would say based on that
that they have some experience of time,
that would be what allowed some of them to fall.
Right, as far as we talk about falling.
but that doesn't necessarily mean that.
There is some means of repentance.
Yeah.
Because again, it is different than how humans experience time.
All right.
Well, that wraps up the first half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits, where we do experience
time.
We're going to go ahead and take short break, and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, we'll be back in a moment to take
your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2-
3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF radio.
The top 10 reasons to attend the Ancient Faith Men's Retreat.
Number 1.
Fellowship with other Orthodox Christian men.
Number 2.
Hearing from four speakers, all priests, and one higher among.
Number 3.
Daily Mattens and Vespers plus Acidist on Friday and Divine Liturgy on Sunday.
Number four.
4.
Supplication at the relics of St. Raphael and learning about his life in the Antiochian
Village Museum.
5.
Giving Back to Antiochian Village through a service project.
6.
Enjoying the beautiful grounds of Antiochian Village, including the meditation trail and hikes.
7.
Football During Free Time.
8.
Delicious Breakfast Lunch and Dinner.
9.
Bonfires and Smoors Each Night.
number 10, the oper-
opportunity to learn and be encouraged in what it means to be a man.
August 22nd through the 25th, 2024 at Antiochian Village in Bolivar, Pennsylvania.
For more information and to register, just click on the banner on the Ancient Faith website
homepage or the lead graphic on the AFM app.
We really hope to see you there.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you are
a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody. Second half of Lord of Spirits Podcasts.
You're on August 1st, 2024. You're talking about that they're men's retreat.
Oh, I'm not going to be there. Well, this is the you like, you as
representative of ancient faith hive mind.
Oh, yeah.
Cause I run everything.
So, right.
Well, you're connected to the whole collective.
I think you should give away shammies.
I'm not saying you have to go all in on the money and get like,
sham, wow, but just a nice shammie clock.
Yeah.
Now goes to a men's retreat, come home with a shammie.
He's gonna be a happy guy.
He's his friends next year.
Look what I got here.
Yeah.
You put it in your face?
It was like, well, go on it.
or something. Yeah, there you go. Oh, there's Ryan is car worst
emerge ever. Anyway, we are talking about time and we do have some
people were calling us. I don't know. It's crazy. People want
to talk to us. So we want to experience a succession of calls.
I know. I know. So we've got James, who's a phone at least
just from New Mexico. So James, welcome, Lord of Spirits
podcast. Thank you so much for having me, Father. Yeah. Yeah.
What's on your?
I'm not an alcoholic.
I just, I kept the number.
I used to live in Albuquerque.
But I'm currently in Denver,
Denver, Colorado right now.
So you did take a left turn at Albuquerque.
I did. I did.
Went up through the mountains.
When you were in Albuquerque,
did you work for a drug cartel
distributing methamphetamine?
I can either have firm norgonite.
Wow.
I
That's, I mean, that's about it. There's not much else to do.
Okay. That need all the people like to continue.
Throwing his old hometown under the bus there.
So James, what's, uh, what's cracking?
So I had a good draw reference.
I so tomorrow, even there is going to be a debate amongst two Protestants
on the concept of open sea.
And I have heard that there are some Orthodox theologians that have concepts that are similar to the concept of open theism.
One that comes to mind is Father Sergei Volkhaakov. I don't know if I'm pronouncing that correctly.
But I was just wondering what the Orthodox conception is to the response of the extreme understanding of libertarian free will and open theism and kind of
kind of...
a good response to that?
Or, I don't know, what do you guys think about that?
Yeah.
We talked about opathy as I'm a little bit in the first half.
But I mean, it's fatal flaw really, right?
Is this idea that God is not only bound by time,
but that He's less, you know, that He doesn't know things.
He's finite.
Yeah, He's finite.
God is less than, right?
And that's,
fundamentally not the God of the Holy Scriptures, not the God of Christianity. I mean, I get why people are into open
theism, assuming they're doing a good faith, right? It's because they want to sort of let God off the hook for
stuff that they don't want to blame him for, you know, I get that right. But that to me,
frankly is a cop out.
I understand, I get it, but it's a cop out. It's an attempt not to really wrestle with
trying to understand what God has actually revealed himself to be doing and who he really is.
But ultimately, it has a basic theological problem, which is, as we said, the God is finite,
therefore. Like, why would you then want to worship a finite creature? And let's just some kind of
pagan because that's what pagans do, is they worship finite beings, or just, you know, really big.
right I don't know if I'll just do anything else.
want to add. Yeah, I mean that's that's that's basically true, that it's a finite being. So it
is like one of the gods of the polypias, right? It's not the Christian God. Um, but part so part of
what engenders it is that, you know, especially in the United States, right, the undercurrent of our
whole culture is Calvinist Puritanism. And so even the folks who out there, especially the evangelical
world.
who are most anti-Calvinist, still accept all the Calvinist presuppositions.
So it's sort of like what we've said before where we're talking about modernism and pointed out
that fundamentalism is a modernism. It's not a really opposed to modernism because fundamentalism
accepts all the presuppositions of modernism but then tries to use the same methodology to come
to the opposite conclusions.
So this is our criticism of a lot of forms of young earth creationism that we've said in the past, right?
People will take all of the assumptions of modern science and all of the methodology of modern science
except at all, and then try to use those methodologies of those tools to come to the opposite results that most scientists do.
Instead of critiquing the methodology itself and critiquing the presuppositions themselves.
Yeah, right. Yeah.
And so open theism happens when you accept the idea that everything that happens in the world ever at all
God is somehow the agent of it
Right
Okay, if God is who Christians say they are say he is then
Everything that happens God is the agent so in horrible hideous awful things happen
God is the agent of them, right?
That's the conclusion that a lot of Calvinists, if you pit them down, will just come out and say, yes.
Right? Yes. God is the agent of that. God decreed that. That would happen.
Right?
And so, the person who becomes an open-theist is like, well, that's horrible.
Right? I don't want God to be the agent of rape and murder and evil.
Right? But they've accepted those Calvinists presuppositions.
So they say
Well, therefore God must not be the agent of any of these things. Right? God must be powerless
in the face of these things. God must be unable to do that. Right? That's the only way they can see
to sort of get God off the hook. Yeah. And what they're failing to attack some of the basic
premises and we were talking about when we brought up over these.
some of those basic premises, like the basic premise that God can make a decree,
quote unquote, before something happens.
That's an incorrect view of the relationship between God and time.
Both the person who says, God knows today what will happen tomorrow,
And the open theist who says God doesn't know
today what will happen tomorrow. Agree on a basic presupposition that God exists today.
Right? God exists within time. And if we accept that He doesn't,
right? If we accept that God acts and God's actions manifest themselves in time,
right? That means that not everything that manifests in time and space of the world is God's action.
There are things that are the results of human action, for example.
Right?
Sometimes at the goading of the demonic and the evil comes into the world, but it's through
human action, not through God's action.
So I think that is our response to open the answer.
It was number one, that's not the true God.
created a God that is like one of the pagan gods.
That's not the God of Christianity of the Christian religion
Which can't be said forcefully enough
And and trying to talk to an open theist about the Holy Trinity is good luck with that
but
So they've crafted this to the God but then also right this bad priest opposition
right and this is a kind of
kind of
problem in Calvinism is the depiction of God not as God acting in his
creation and acting powerfully where no one can prevent it but God is behind
the scenes pulling strings maneuvering things into place where people all
think they're making decisions but they aren't really God is kind of
puppeteering them right. That view of God is frankly nowhere in the
Scriptures. Right. And...
Does it make a heck of a lot of logical sense either?
Yep, right.
Yeah.
All right, does that help James?
Hey, Dallas, yes it does.
Thank you so much.
Great, all right, thanks for calling.
Okay, next we've got William of Tennessee.
William of Tennessee, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you, Father, this is good to be here.
Yes, so what's the word on a mountain top?
Intentive C.
the three. Yeah. No, and I very much do not want to kill a bar, not even
one of the three. Okay.
You have to wonder though about that football team in the Tennessee Titans. I
mean, from a, you know, Titans, right? This is, you know, chained up in
Tardarus kind of thing. Just throwing that out there. But anyway, it is the oilers
doesn't make any sense though. That's true.
Alright, anyways, William, what's going on?
Speaking of titans and paganism, at the beginning of the episode, Father Stephen went on the
diet tribe about the myth of the great through line of Western civilization, ancient Sumer,
continuous line to whoever we like right now.
My question is this story which has tried to fuse Christianity and paganism and now
they're pulling it apart.
the difference between this and universal history.
which seems to take things like the Trojan War and the North Edas and stuff and bring them into the Christian story.
Yeah, this is a great question.
So, right, so, okay, history, right?
History is a thing.
And it's ultimately a story of a people, right?
So it's about how all these other stories feed into the story of us here and now.
Okay. That is not the
same thing as saying that there is this metaphysical linear progression of time that, you know,
everything ultimately belongs to or something like that, right?
And also I think one of the things that's quite different between traditional Christian
universal history and what's going on with 19th century, frankly German Lutheranism and
you know that kind of philosophical
tradition is that the approach that traditional Christianity has to that is the approach that
for instance St. Justin Martyr has, which is the idea that there are seeds of the logos,
these things ultimately are not, it's not that they're consistent, they're not consistent,
there's a sifting going on, right? There's conversion going on, right? You can't keep
everything right you can't pretend that ancient pagan
is equal to Christianity.
And St. Basil the Great, of course, in his famous address to young men on the uses of Greek
literature, he goes on exactly about how you do this.
It's worth reading.
It's on the internet.
You can read it.
This is not the same thing as saying, everything leads up to this point in history and we are the
pinnacle of history.
That's not what that's saying at all.
So the question is, what is the goal?
And how do you understand the road?
getting there, right? And also then there's the metaphysical stuff which very much determines
how you read all of that. So that's how I'd say that the difference between the tradition,
Christian tradition of universal history is, and this idea of kind of the end of history that
you get which comes in with 19th century German Christianity. So I don't know, Father,
what do you got to say about any of that? Well, I barely know Rick Roper, if that's his real name.
And...
I don't have time for silliness at his videos, so I feel no need to defend him.
But yeah, I mean, I think there's an important, so from my perspective, right, when I'm looking
at the way like the scriptures interact with pagan myth, right, they don't on the one
hand say, oh, this is all made up nonsense.
Forget about it, right?
But they don't on the other...
hand say, this is all true and is all part of the same tradition that we're a part of. Right?
There is a constant latent critique and correction, right, and readdress. Like, yes, there's a flood
that happened. You've heard all these stories about it, but here's what really happened. And often,
the details, as expressed in scripture, are inversions of the pagan stories. Yeah.
or rather from the person
perspective of the Christian tradition, the pagan stories are an inversion of the truth.
Right? So when I look at, say, the famous statue of Athena, where wisdom is being embodied by the sculptor in ancient Greece,
This wisdom is embodied as a half-naked woman standing next to us serpent.
I see
something going on there from the perspective of my Christian tradition. And what's going on there is not
oh see this is all part of our growth toward our perfect modern-day religion. This is another step
down the same road as the Hebrew Bible. I see this as oh look the benign people of Greece were
worshipping demons, right? And their depiction of wisdom.
looks an awful lot like Eve listening to the serpent and this is their depiction of what it means to be wise.
Right. And that's probably not coincidental.
Yeah, the details are really important here.
So that to me, right, you know, rip hunter, whatever he's doing with Pazzo, I don't know.
but he doesn't own universal history but what I put that on.
That's why well that's the name I always hear associated with it. Yeah, yeah is Rick roll so
But yeah, so I think that's that to me is the key difference between what's going on with Western civilization
I think in that the myth of Western civilization. There's a heavy dose of perennialism in it
Yeah, that I don't think is a part of
The actual Christian tradition yeah
Yeah.
Does that help William?
I think so.
The difference between baptizing these verses,
just the pernulous take all of it itself
and it culminates in the end of history.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then I did have a question on topic
if there is time, at least on the topic of the episode.
All right.
We've got nothing for time.
Two for one deal here.
I will take it.
here I will take it.
So this is, and it's probably be talked about more in this path as well with our Calvinist
friends who, because they see how they see gods on nipotence and omniscience and his
role as the creator ultimately means that he creates certain people for the purpose
or not for the purpose, well they would say for the purpose of domination because they
would say that he creates some people.
knowing that in the last
judgments that person will be
among the goats and not the sheep.
And if I were a Calvinist in
response to the God-existing
end time and knowing we'll come
ahead, I would say, well, I can
say God exists outside of time
and is looking down like on a
game board, knowing the past,
present and future, all
simultaneous.
but he also created creation, and knows how everything is and will develop at the last judgment.
So, how we critique their understanding of time that leads them and agency, I suppose,
that leads them to the conclusion of God create certain people for damnation.
What do you think father, you're the one who's got the expertise in Calvinism?
The problem is the view of God being up above time and looking down on it isn't really him being outside of
Isn't the same thing as temporal categories not applying to him
Right in the sense that let's use our space metaphor
Right
Someone could say the same thing about God's relationships of space. We as God isn't in any particular place on earth
He's up above in heaven somewhere looking down on the universe
right and we will see.
Well, no, that's not really what God's omnipresence means.
That's not really what we mean when we say
that doesn't apply to God, right?
Because again, we're picturing him like he's a big human
somewhere looking at the whole thing.
Like we can only see this part, but God could see the whole thing.
But he's seeing it, he's knowing it, he's thinking about it the same way we do.
Right. So there
there's still an anthropomorphizing going on there.
There's still a subjecting God to our human limitations.
Right.
So there's also an issue here with this idea of,
and we've talked about this in terms of what the will is,
that there's a whole complex of
Please.
positions going on here. One of them is that having a free will means I could choose to do A or I could
choose to do not A or even opposite of A. That's what free will means. And so if I'm not totally free
to do anything then I don't have free will. Now of course that doesn't make any sense.
Right, because there's all kinds of things I'm not free to do like fly.
I mean, not just flying under my own power.
Trust me when I go to an airport, right?
I'm sorry.
The idea of me being able to actually fly anywhere is a pipe dream.
Right.
Steven has many amusing and horrifying stories about your traveling stuck in airports, right?
I don't want to be stuck in airports, right?
And I still have free will, but I can't get out, right?
My favorite one is the one that has the climax of, and then the looting.
started. Yeah, but we don't need to get into that anyway. But so there's all kinds of
and at any given moment in time, there's a relatively limited number of things I even
theoretically could choose to do. Right? And I say theoretically, there's all kinds of
things I could theoretically do that are just absurd. You know, I could grab a pen and shove
it in my eye. But why would I write? Why would I do that? I mean, technically, I'm free
to do that, right? But like...
don't want to. Right? And why would I? Right? So when we talk about the will, we're talking
primarily about the natural will. Right? So having free will means being free to flourish,
to become fully human, to develop into the person that God created you to be. And so sin,
me being able to sin is not freedom.
Me being able to sin is last.
freedom because sin will stop me from growing and achieving that. That's why sin
enslaves us. That's why, and this is a big point that St. Max the Confessor makes,
is that in the Eskitan, in the life of the world to come, we will be totally free,
and we will be totally free because we are not able to sin. Right? And that phrase,
Please.
It runs a foul of like all the presuppositions in any kind of Calvinism debate.
Right?
That I am at my most free when I cannot sin. Right? That breaks all the presuppositions.
Because it's a fundamentally different understanding of freedom and the will and sin.
Yeah, that that isn't held so.
That's a pre-supposition that has to be broken down.
So the idea is that the person who God has reprobated, the person who God has created in order to condemn him to eternal torment for his own glory, which is what Calvinism teaches.
Okay, that is what Calvinism teaches. It's not that he knows. Right? That's our minianism.
Right, is that God knows.
Calvinism, God creates people in order as vessels of wrath,
in order to get them into eternal punishment for his own glory.
What Calvinism teaches, right?
The basic idea there is that that person is unable to repent,
because for Calvinists, all people are unable to repent.
God has to come and make you repent.
He does it to you.
right? Literally against your will, because your will is completely sinful. He
repents you. Right. And so there are, you know, you can really get into the
weeds here. So like Abraham Kuiper's idea of eternal justification and things
like this in real time. But what all of these things have in common is that God
is making some decrease regarding
people's eternal destiny before he creates them. And it doesn't really matter if it's
temporarily before or logically before. There's still a flow of time and God is standing
at one point in it. Right. And so it's not logically coherent at that point. Right.
You
to, to understand that way, it's subjecting God to our sort of human logic and our human
experience of time.
Anyway, you slice it in order to try to argue the point.
And if you don't do that, you can't argue the point.
Right.
So, if you say to one of our Calvinist friends, okay, I want you to argue to me for predestination
reprobation.
without using the term before.
You can't do it.
You can't argue for it without saying God blank before He blank.
You can't.
And so it's impossible to argue for without presupposing
a relationship between God and times, it's inaccurate.
Yeah, I mean, well, that's why they just often throw in phrases like,
in such a way as.
That's my favorite.
Yes, the quasi-queedom.
You know, anyway.
I hope that helps, William.
It's somewhat, but my brain is still breaking.
Yeah, this isn't easy stuff.
I'm going to get it right now.
This is not easy stuff.
All right, all right.
Well, okay, we're going to go ahead and move on with the second half of the
Laura Sweets.
What are we talking about anyway? Oh, that's right. Time. Yeah.
Time in the Bible. How does how does time manifest in the Scripture in terms of God and time and
Scripture? Well, when we let out left off before the exciting commercial break, yeah,
that's two Genesis. What do you think? We were talking about the days of creation.
Sort of. Yeah. And so, yeah, we will we will return there. And so we've talked about this before,
right and
Part of our understanding of the relationship between God and time comes from this, comes
from understanding what's going on here in Genesis chapter 1 through 2 verse 2, right?
In terms of the days of creation, right?
Let's just bring up St. Augustine and each half.
St. Augustine points out that God can't do something on a day, right?
At first people go, what?
that by the way in his literal interpretation of Genesis.
Yes, right.
That's the title of the work.
Yeah.
He says, of course, God can't do something on a day.
Well, what does he mean by that?
Because it seems like it's saying God did things on a day.
Right?
Well, here's what he means.
Again, God does not start each day with like a to-do list.
Okay, today I'm going to separate...
I'm going to create...
I'm going to separate it from darkness. That's going to take me 24 hours. Right?
Really? Okay. Well, no, that's silly. That's not what it's saying. Right? That like it takes 24 hours
to grow out to do these things and he does them in order. Right? Like we all kind of understand that's not how any of this works. Right?
That's what St. Augustine means. Why? Of course, God doesn't like do something on that day and it becomes especially absurd
of course.
we've talked about before on the show, when you get to day seven, right?
Day seven. And this is another note. See, I'm trying to be, I'm trying to be
friendly with our young earth creationist friends tonight, relatively.
Guys, stop it with the seven literal 24 hour days.
Cause saying that the seventh day is a literal 24 hours is silly.
Okay, say six. Say six. Okay.
point with six because the idea that again on the seventh day God didn't do anything for
24 hours.
Look, he'd had a long week.
Right.
Like that doesn't make sense.
Okay.
If God didn't do anything for 24 hours, like how did things keep existing?
And you know, right?
Like what?
Yeah.
That doesn't really make sense.
It's clearly not what's going on.
God was not tired.
right? And we've talked before on the show about how what's going on with the
rested is more that he sat down that he was enthroned, right? So the seventh day
is the day of his kingdom, his reign, his rule, because we talked about that
on the show before too. Kingdom is a noun, English like Latin,
reifies everything. We think of it as a thing, but this is more of a verbal idea.
God's domain, His rule, when we talk about the kingdom of God.
Right? That's on the seventh day. God has seated. He is enthroned. His reign, right, is there on the Sabbath day, which is the seventh day, the last day.
And so much of what you read as you go through the Torah and then through the rest of the Hebrew scriptures is people wanting to enter into God's rest, to enter into his kingdom, to enter into his rule.
Right?
Each of the days of creation is God.
work manifesting itself as a day, six of them, right? And then on the seventh day,
God's kingdom manifests itself as a day. And that is a day which seteth not as the
prophet say, the kingdom's day, which seteth not. Right? That is at the end of the
week. That is where we're describing for. And then when we get to the very beginning
of the New Testament and we get into the gospels, right? What do we find? The
kingdom of God is near. The kingdom of God is at hand. It is approaching. It is
It's here.
right? That's seven days. That doesn't mean that like, oh, God's going to be in charge again now.
Yeah, like he wasn't, right? Yeah, right. No, and it did mean the other six days he wasn't in charge,
right? Again, that's the, we know it doesn't mean that, right? We know that this is the day that
that is manifest, right?
And so the creation receives a day of rest,
where
our enthronement and his rule is kingdom manifests itself.
And this is all the Sabbaths are pointing to this in the Old Testament.
And this is why we have the Lord's Day, which is not the Sabbath, the Sabbath is Saturday.
The Lord's Day is the first day of the week at Sunday.
Going back to our Western civilization thing, us and not the English speakers, have pagan days for the days of the week,
unlike every other sub
supposedly Christian country in the world that calls Saturday the Sabbath and Sunday the Lord's Day.
I mean, even Spanish, they're right next door.
They got Sabano and Domingo. Like, come on, man. Like anyway.
What the Lord's Day was at the beginning of the week.
Right? Because of the king to be established in Christ is enthroned at the ascension.
the Rascension episode.
Right?
Um.
But so what we see here is, again, part of God's relationship with time, right?
And that includes a couple pieces here, the one piece being God's work, God's activity, God's energies manifesting themselves, right?
At days and times, as days and in days and times and seasons and places, right?
And then also, right, we see the cycle of the
the disciples of the disciples of the
disciples of the disciples of the
disciples of the Feasts.
They are laid out first in the Torah
and then in the rest of the
What all of these cycles, what these calendars really?
Right? These calendars are, is they're an imposition of order
and structure in order to shape human experience. What do I mean by that? So these things aren't like
objective, right? Like a culture could say, hey, you know what? We're going to have 30 day months
in three 10 day weeks.
Right? Like, that one, you know, ripped the fabric of reality apart, right? Like, that would,
right? I say this is, you know, we've got folks of the Orthodox Church who are out of the
old calendar, the new calendar, we disagree about what the date is today, right?
But neither of us can sort of appeal to some object.
fact, right? No, objectively today is August 1st, right? Like, how would you argue that?
Or prove that, right? So these are structures imposed, right? Structures imposed on the created
order. And these structures that are intended then to order human life and human experience
You
such a way is to produce a particular result in order to shape humanity in a certain way
if they're followed, if these disciplines and structures are followed and lived out.
And what you've actually got, we've talked about this before on the show, is in the calendars,
whether we're talking about the calendar laid out in the Torah or the church's calendar,
there's two sort of layers.
So there's one layer that is...
based around the agricultural cycle, right? Seed time in harvest, right? And this cycle has its
own new year, Roche-Sanada, the head of the year, the first of the year, right? Roughly September
1st, Tishri 1, right? On the Jewish calendar, the agricultural cycle calendar begins in September,
ends at the end of August. And that one, right?
is not sort of arbitrary. Right? You can't go in plant crops in the winter and try to harvest them in the summer.
Yeah, this is just how the natural world works. You have to adapt to it.
Or vice versa. Right. So the agricultural cycle itself does have this kind of existence within the order of the creation. Right.
but by
by God attaching feasts to the elements of this calendar, whether it's the new year, whether
it's the offering of the first fruits of the harvest, whether it's the celebration of
the harvest proper coming in, right? All of these feasts give these sort of significance
vis-a-vis God, right? They bring the necessary relationships of humanity.
in the creative order, created order are brought up into a relationship with God.
So this is sort of bottom up, right? It's going from day to day life, right? Working in the farm,
which is what almost everyone was doing, right? Subsistence farming. Bringing that up into connection with
the life of God, right? And then in addition to that bottom up calendar, you've got what we could
can describe as a top down cow.
which is the calendar centered around Paska, around Passover.
And remember when God gives the Passover, he says,
this will be for you the first of months.
So there's two first months for the two different overlapping calendars.
But that cycle of feast, the Passover, Pentecost,
that cycle of feast based around Paska and Passover,
Those are not based on sort of natural...
circles of nature like the harvest, those are based on acts of God that manifested
themselves in the world at particular times and places like the Exodus from Egypt, like
the giving of the covenant of Mount Sinai, like the resurrection of Christ, like the coming
of the Holy Spirit. Right? So that's why I say this is sort of top down. This is sort
of God acting in creation.
And so you have on one...
One hand, the structure of life and creation, you have on the other hand, the structure of
divine life that God wants to share with humanity.
When you bring those two calendars together, when you follow them and are structured by
its discipline, what you have is what we call theosis.
That the life of humans in the creative, created world, their real life, their everyday
life, of trying to grow enough food to feed their families, right?
and dainities of human life.
are elevated and brought up into relationship with God and God shares his life with humans.
Those two things are wedded together structurally.
And so as that cycle is practiced again and again giving order to humans' experience of
time, experience of the year, of the week, of the months.
structures, humans again and again re-enter into.
the works of God, right? God's energy is these great acts of God, right? Because the Passover is not
remembering what God did when he brought the Israelites out of Egypt. It's participating in it. Yeah.
Right? This is the night when God brought us out of Egypt.
Today is the day of resurrection, right?
Reentering into that. Right. And so
time here in terms of its structuring becomes.
but in and of itself the means of of theosis through worship and celebration.
Now we've got to shift gears a little, right? We're going for a little testament to New Testament.
In terms of things regarding time in the Bible, now we've got to pick on our Calvinists friends a little more.
Sorry guys. It's always time. And most of you are guys, I gotta say. There are some
God, I'm gonna swim out there.
say a nun, but I'm trying to think of any, I mean, I know they exist. A lot of those
Calvinists men have wives. So I mean, if that, if you build children who are being raised
as the reformed fate. So there are bloody people count as other. But so the, when we get
two concepts of
predestination as they're expressed, right? I say Paul especially in like Romans and and Ephesians.
What we're talking about so the word that's usually translated as predestination is actually pro-Orizzo
in Greek, which means to put something in order in advance.
It doesn't mean to declare something in advance. There's other words for that. It doesn't even mean to
Decrease something to make something happen in advance
Predestined of course applies this idea of destiny than fatalism that I know most of our Calvinist friends
Would say that's a bad framing that's a pagan framing of what they believe so we'll issue that
But again, what is this talking about?
Well, if you look closely at what St. Paul is talking about in Romans, for example,
when St. Paul uses it, right? For those God-forward knew, he also predestined to be conformed to the likeness of his son, right?
For example, right?
We understand that this means put an order in advance.
Right? If we read this as...
For those God for new and we'll talk about for knowledge here in a second, those people,
he put things in order in advance for them to be conformed to the likeness of his son.
The way our Calvinist friends would like us to read that is, God decided that those people
he for new would be the people as opposed to other people who work and form to the likeness
of his son.
Yeah, rather than...
that he set things up right so that yeah right and to me the more natural reading of this is not that
the more natural reading of this which doesn't have any of the problems we've been talking about
recently in terms of God in time right is that God set things in order in advance so that these people
could be conformed to the length.
of his son. Yeah, which means he provided the way of salvation. Right. He provided the way
of salvation and the means of salvation and all of that. Right. And, right. As St. Paul is talking
to these people, right, as he says in Romans in the same epistle, right. He says, while we will
still sinners Christ died for us. That thing that had to happen Christ's death and
Resurrect.
action for us to find salvation, right? Not just that. The incarnation, Christ's life,
his death, his resurrection, his ascension and the thrownment. All of that happened while
St. Paul's audience were still sinners, right? So while they were still sinners, God put
all of this in motion, He did all of this. This was manifested in time and in human experience.
perspective before they heard the gospel to the people St. Paul's talking to
before those people he's talking to were the gospel right that was already
set up right. St. Paul goes on in that verse with a
government officer who formed the like this of his son right he says those he
called he also right he says and now God is going to finish this work that he
began right. God already did this before you knew anything about this you can
trust him that he is going to continue the work of your salvation.
But at no point in there to say, Paul say, you don't need to cooperate.
Or you have no choice of the matter.
Or any similar thing.
Or God is doing this to you.
Or the only thing you contribute to your salvation is the sin that you need to be saved
from.
anything remotely like that in any of these passages. Right?
So, this is Saint God put these things in order in advance to make salvation possible, right?
In advance, what does that mean?
Not in advance for God, right?
In advance for you, right?
Like all this happened like 1,943 years before I was born, right?
I am a- it is-
possible for me to find salvation because God did these things, 1,943 years, give or take
before I was born. That's what St Paul said. Right? It's absolutely true and not that
complicated and doesn't involve God being somehow subject to time in a weird way.
Yeah, the before and after is just human experience people.
That's right. Yeah. Right. And we have to keep this in mind when we talk about prophecy.
Because sometimes some Calvinists, not the more nuanced ones, but some of our Calvinist friends,
will say things like, well, if Calvinism is true, that prophecy is impossible,
because God can't know for sure that the prophecy is going to come true. Unless he determines everything.
Right? Well, what's, you know, the manifold problems with that, right? But if, and we've
already go back to our profits episode, most of prophecy is not predicting things that
will happen in the future, okay? But there are places where the profits talk about things
that will happen in the future from the perspective of when they said them.
As humans, right?
Isaiah talks about the restoration of Israel.
Ezekiel talks about the resurrection of Israel,
which were in the future from Ezekiel's perspective,
and his original here is perspective.
So he did talk about future events,
but notice what those future events are.
Those future events are,
God is going to do this thing.
At some point, which for us lies in the future.
Okay.
So.
God does not have to be behind the scenes,
puppet mastering, everything,
and moving everything around in order for him
to be able to do something.
Right.
God can just act.
Right?
There wasn't all these things he needed to do
and puppeteer, make sure we're all right
so that
the logos could be incarnated as our Lord Jesus Christ.
Yeah, because again, that requires that he's bound in some way.
Like God had to set things up this way in order for this and this.
Yeah.
You had to do this laundry list of things in order to be able to do that one.
Like, he had to cooperate with the creasing that he himself made.
No, he could...
I mean, this is one of the things that's different about Jesus in the Gospels,
and you know, that like, isn't it one of the...
It was at the Centurion who comes to him and says,
and asked him to heal a servant and he just...
says you can just command it. Yeah. Right. Which is different than the way that
miraculous healings happen in the ancient world and anyone else is religion. Doesn't have to
employ any tech name, right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You just command. So if God says, you know,
because God doesn't do things at a particular time. Right. So God has a divine energy of love,
different divine energies.
God says one of those is going to be manifest toward Israel in the future.
That's because he's going to manifest it in the future from our perspective future.
Right? We haven't experienced it yet, but we will.
Right? Like again, it's not the way we're used to thinking about it and talking about it.
Right? But it's actually the way the scriptures talk about it and it makes more sense.
doesn't require any of these weird other extra theological constructs, right, to make it work.
So then, for knowledge,
because almost as much as open theus, Arminians basically accept all of the Calvinists presuppositions
to try to get to different results. This is why it's very hard for them to wind a
It depends against Calviness.
I'm going to concede all of your po-
but try to disagree with your conclusion.
Because, again, just saying, oh, well, it's based on God's knowledge, not his will.
Right? God knows in advance what's going to happen.
Means God is standing at a point in time, and there are other points in time which are the future
for God, from God's perspective, or in the future.
Yeah.
And he knows, you know, he
So it's speaking from God's perspective again, we've got a problem, right?
But even more than that, right? Even more than that.
What does it mean to know?
We've talked about the different ways of knowing in a couple of different episodes of this show, right?
So ways of knowing like tech nays away of knowing like know how knowing how to do something because does God know how to do things?
Yeah, God doesn't have to use a technique to do things. Yeah, he can just command just man. Yeah, man. He can just have that if as right.
Right.
Right. Like scientific knowledge, demonstrable knowledge. Right. Because does God know things because he could like do the math and show you his work.
Is this like demonstrably true? Is that how God knows things?
Right? Like, as it makes sense, right? Does God have wisdom in the human sense?
Right, which is knowing the best way to
Be clever and knowing how to navigate life. Well, no, not in that sense, right?
So when we talk about God's knowledge
Including for knowledge or God's wisdom for that matter
right? We're saying that because it is the more correct way to speak.
not meaning it literally.
Right?
It is more correct to say, God knows everything.
By that what we really mean is,
there's nothing that God doesn't know.
See, there's negative statement again, right?
There's nothing God doesn't know.
But he doesn't know things the way we know them.
We don't mean that literally.
We don't mean like, I know a finite set of things
and God knows
be much bigger set of all the things.
Yeah, I mean, we just, we can't conceptualize, again, we don't know what it's like to be God.
We have certain kinds of language that have been used in Scripture and in the tradition of the church,
that we use, but we need to recognize that all language to describe God is contingent.
It's not perfect. It does not encapsulate.
It just sort of points towards.
Right.
You know what I mean?
That's what we got.
It's more correct.
Right. Right. It is more correct in implication to say God knows everything than to say God knows nothing. Right.
Right. Right. There is nothing that God doesn't know. Right. But we don't even know what it means to say that God knows something because he doesn't know things the way we know them. Right.
So yeah, I know we're probably giving people...
headaches. We're gonna come a little more, it's not gonna get easier, but we're gonna
come a little more down to earth by the end of this, I promise.
We're losing people left and right, just too much metaphysics, too much...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Just kidding, actually, there's still a decent number of people that are listening, apparently.
Hello, people who are still with us.
Well, next week episode, you know, we're gonna get some more payoff to some of this stuff
that seems difficult now.
So, before we finish up this second half here, we want to talk about something that we've
talked about before.
This is a little bit of a review, but we're, like he says, talking about the way the scriptures
talk about time, which is what we've been talking about in this second half.
And that's the whole concept of an age.
We talked about this in a previous episode.
We talked about the different ages that are talked about in Scripture, right?
A-one which means of an age, right?
And it's important that we understand, we talked about this at the time too, so it's partially
this is kind of review.
The relationship between the idea of an age and a world, right?
Because that language is used interchangeably by the fathers and in our hemnography, at
least in English translation, right?
So we talk about the life of the world.
to come, we talk about the life of the age to come, we don't mean two different things.
Yeah, there's, in Greek, there's two words. The word gets translated age usually as
Christmas. I mean, sorry, world is a Christmas and then age is a on usually. But yeah, they
don't mean like, we've talked about age in the past that doesn't mean like a specific
period of time necessarily.
And world does not mean like...
the earth or a planet. We have to get that out of our head. That certain modern definition,
right? We hear world and we think like planet. Yeah, right? And strange new worlds. And Cosmos,
Cosmos doesn't even really mean universe either. It means it, you know, it's the order is really
kind of literally what it means. And actually, by the way, I see I don't have my jingle ready to go,
this is the origin of our word cosmetics, because the idea is that things being put in order,
you know.
Yeah, yeah. And so we're talking about the created order, the order of the created world,
when we talk about the world, the order of creation, and a particular order, a particular
ordering is referred to as an age. And so when we talked about the different ages, we talked about
the age before the fall. We talked about the age before the flood, right? Where there's a particular
ordering of the
creation and then like with the flood how that ordering was undone and then there was a new order of creation a new age after the flood and
how there's
the beginning of the new covenant the new testament begins a new age and then there is the age to come the world to come that
Order that will come after the final judgment when God has set all things
permanently and finally in order and
And part of the reason why we get in our English translations, the bleedover is
through as we talked about in that episode, the Latin concept of the Seculum, which was
adapted by St. Augustine, he keeps coming up today in his city of God to refer to the
sort of ever-changing, shifting world in which we live.
And so the idea is that the age to come, the world to come, the Seculum to come, the Seculum
secular. I'm ready.
Ages of Ages, right? That we talk about in the future is an age that has no end.
Yeah, and that's why you get, you know, an English tradition, a particular part of the
English tradition that phrase, world without end, which gets used to translate secular,
secular, secular, secular law on my camera with a Latin, which is the Latin translation of
Aeol. East to Ceyona's coming on on. Yeah. Yeah. Which by the way everybody, when we sing and
and unto the ages of ages in so many of our Orthodox hymns.
and petitions and stuff, it doesn't mean, and for a really long time, it means this,
it means, and into the life of the world to come, and into the age that has no end,
that is the age to come. That's what that means.
And so when David Bentley heart points out that A-on means of the age, he is correct,
right? The problem is
is he wants to make that distinction partially.
So he wants to say when the scriptures talk about the condemnation of the age, we'll see
it's of the age, so that means it's just for a finite period of time.
Now the verse before when it talks about the life of the age, he doesn't want to say
that's a finite period of time.
But aside from that inconsistency, right?
the fact that it says of the age of that age really because it's a demonstrative
pronoun of that age of the age to come right that says nothing about how long
that age is. It doesn't say whether that age has an end or not his translation.
He's using a little bit of ledger domain to imply to you the reader of his
books if you're so inclined.
to try to make you think, oh well since it means of the age, that's a finite period of time.
But the word age does not imply that that age has an end necessarily. You would have to predicate
that. Does this age have an end or not? Yeah. Right. Which is something you'd have to get from
context and more biblical interpretation. It's not something implied by the word, even though he's
making an English implication. Yeah. The age to come is an age that has no end. It is the
The King.
of the day which seteth not. Yeah. Yeah. So so he's right that the word means that particular
thing, but not right in the way he's using that for. He's making an implication. Yeah.
Yeah. That people are taking from it. We had that implications not actually supported by the
definition of the word. Right. Exactly. The whole point is that this age has no end. The age to come.
So, alright, but this half of the podcast does have an end because...
We experience time, and we're going to go ahead and take our second final break for this
episode of Laura Spirits' podcast, and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You've probably heard of St. Rafael Halloweeny, St. Alexander Hodovitsky, liturgical translator
Isabel Habgood, and other righteous men and women who made their mark on the early
development of Orthodoxy in America.
But what about the notorious, itinerant Bulgarian monk, or Father Rafael Morgan, the first
Black Orthodox priest in America?
Or Vera Johnston, who served the Orthodox Church without renouncing her theosifist roots.
stories and many others.
Some edifying, some appalling, all entertaining, make up the lost histories of the early
decades of Orthodox Christianity in the continental United States.
Lost histories, the good, the bad, and the strange in early American Orthodoxy by Matthew
name out now at store.enginefaith.com. Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
We've got a bunch of people who have called in.
We're going to take just a couple calls.
All of them.
Oh no.
No!
Everyone
No, everyone.
Wipe them out. Anyway.
Yes, we have Radu who called us from the great white North and
Welcome to Lord Spirits podcast, Radu
And it's good to be here called this thing for having me. Yeah, sure. What's what's on your mind?
I want to first I want to first hear a good thing about younger aspirations too, which is that about 10 years ago
I want to Ken Ham's art experience.
Jackie and it was one of the most entertaining $44 I ever spent in my life. I would go
to the gym. Confirmed. I need to go there. Oh man. I love Christian Kitch so much. Like I
want to go there and I also have a big ambition to see the precious moments chapel and I think
it's in Carthage, Illinois if I remember correctly. Oh man. Carthage, Jenny, I'm Dillinda
It's a real thing. The precious movement's chapel, everybody, look it up.
not making this up. Anyway. My question is, Father, how scriptures and the
fathers talk differently about the finitude of angels than the
incinitude of God? And you said earlier, well, okay, God isn't anywhere, it's not
in time. And the things can be said about a model of spirit, right? It's not anywhere.
It's not this place in space. You said this in previous episodes. They're not. It
a bit on it.
experience time like we did now, experience a succession of moments. So how, if at all,
the scripture talk about the synod of angels in time and space or some other way different
than God and or how do we think about that so that I don't end up stumbling into talking
about angels and therefore small G gods as being infinite blind mistake in the same way
got it. Yeah so
St. John DeMascus, who's kind of our go to for a lot of this stuff, he provides a really helpful summary in
his book, The Exact Exhibition of the Orthodox Faith, or sometimes just called on the Orthodox Faith. There's a section there on angels and demons
and what he says about this
is that
angels are
circumscribed, in other words that they have
you know that they're bound in some way they're finite. He said but only God knows exactly.
the form of their limitation.
So, this is actually helpful because in a number of ways and one of the ways is that we often
talk about, and this is, you know, in a lot of places in North of Oxford, we talk about
the angels as being bodyless, right?
But he makes the point essentially that they are compared to us, they are bodyless.
But compared to God, they're not.
Right?
So compared to us, they have no...
body, but compared to God, they're fully embodied. Dense is a brick by comparison. That only
God is truly limitless. The point is that they're limited, but humans can't understand their
limitation. Only God can understand their limitation. That's what St. John of Damascus says in his
summary about all this stuff. Do I leave anything out, Father? I mean, I'm not going to, oh, I'm
actually say John of Damascus.
He'd say.
But yeah, it's that.
Right, angels are so beyond us that we sort of can't see their limits because there's so much
Beyond our limits, right like they're not limited in the ways we are
Yeah, but God being above them obviously as creations
Knowes their limitations. Yeah, I mean, we have language to talk about this, but there's no
Definition exactly does that make sense Redu?
Yeah, I mean, just a little clarifying question on that.
But so you said earlier, well, God is quite clear on you,
says that the way he's in the temple doesn't mean
that he's not somewhere else.
He's not contained in temples made as human hands.
From the pagan perspective, when they
would talk about Artemis of somewhere,
or Zeus of somewhere, in all localization of a god
in a place, did they, the pagan gods in that kind of myth
and worldview make similar claims,
such as because Zeus is here, does mean Zeus,
than also bear and you shouldn't.
be Hollywood Zeus because Zeus is everywhere or how would that compare?
No Zeus does not claim to be everywhere.
Right?
For instance with the Olympians, okay, there's a clear division of territory.
You've got Zeus who's the Sky God and then you've got Poseidon who has the Seas and Hades
who has the underworld and there's a sense in which if those gods cross those boundaries
there. Now these guys are all
bruh.
right? If they cross the boundaries they're really doing something bad because that's not their territory. Right? So, so this is one of the things that's unique about Yahweh is he truly is said to be everywhere.
Yeah, right? He's the God not just of Israel but of all the nations.
Yeah, that's why for instance it says over and over again our God is in heaven and on earth
And even references to him being in the depth of the sea like these are all
Pokes in the eye of paganism
when this is said about God.
Yeah.
And now there's the God of all the nations, as you said.
Now the pagans did believe and the language that's used
in the literature is hyphostasis.
We've talked about this before.
Don't flip out.
It's not the same thing as the Trinity listeners.
But did they believe they had multiple localizations
of the same God?
Right.
So they could be in multiple places.
But that's not the same as being everywhere.
Right. There were multiple localizations. This temple, that temple, the other temple. Right. Ray is the sun god
So Ray is the sun, but he's also this idol. He's also kind of Pharaoh, depending on what time period we're talking about in Egypt
Right each of those is an embodiment of the same God, right? But there's a finite number of those embodiments
Yeah, and it isn't where those embodiments aren't
Yeah
Yeah, yeah, I mean a lot of pigons had the notion that
you could essentially leave the territory of a God to escape them.
You know, you can see this in the scriptures where there's where some of the pagans talk
about Israel in pagan terms. They're like, oh, their God is a God of the mountains and
the hills. I think that's one of the things that's said about him. Like, oh, we don't go
in those mountains because their God is kind of around there.
You know?
Well, in Jonah tries to run away.
Yeah, exactly. Jonah treats God as a pagan.
Does it go so well?
Yeah, so what do you think, Redu? Does that help you out there?
As much as I think I can ever understand, yes.
That's pretty great actually. So good job, Father Steven.
All right, thank you very much for calling. We're going to take one more call.
Two more. All right, we'll take two more calls because Father Steven is practically begging for me
me to do that.
We've got Antonio for you, the listener.
Oh, flash collar.
All right, so Antonio, welcome to the Laura Spirits podcast.
What's on your mind?
How are we going?
I just, first of all, one of, thank you guys
for the show with very informative.
And my question is basically concerning the Maseroth
if I'm saying it right.
And I'm the agent, I think Joe 38,
32 speaks about bringing up.
a certain celestial body in the season.
It seems that from second temple writings
that it says that the angels actually have some type of control
and the turning of these certain celestial bodies
and their certain alignments with the earth.
And those are the ages.
So it seems like time.
to me, I heard an interpretation by Michael Heiser about when they were in exile.
Jewish people were in exile.
When Ezekiel has a vision that God is on the throne and it's like the four cardinal
points of the Babylonian zodiac, you know, that he didn't control the time.
So what does he have view on all that?
I'm not sure if you touched on this in previous episode.
What do you think, Father?
I know we talked about the constellations and Ezekiel's vision in a previous episode, right?
And so there is, right?
When you read, like in Deuteronomy, the celestial bodies which are associated with angels,
mark the times and seasons, right?
But that is always related to, and you can really see this, for example, in the book of Inek,
that is directly...
related to the calendar, like we were talking about in the last half, right? That's sort
of what marks out the calendar, right? So, like when is POSCA? Right? Well, you determine
when POSCA is every year based on the first full moon after the Vernil Equinox, right?
So if you understand that
The moon is under the operation, shall we say, of an angelic being, right?
And the sun is to produce the equinox, right?
If that's your understanding, then those angelic beings are sort of marking time
to keep that calendar on schedule, which then, as we talked about,
that calendar, assuming humans submit to that ordering.
participate in the calendar and participate in the cycle of feasts and the worship and
have their lives formed by it, then that becomes sort of a vehicle of salvation.
And so the angelic beings associated with those heavenly bodies with the constellations,
the planets, the stars, the sun and the moon become sort of the intermediaries of the
calendar that the means.
through which God reveals the calendar and those cycles
wrecked to humans. Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah, that's some good information.
It kind of sounds a little bit like a Galatians chapter two
a little bit.
Yeah, when he speaks about, when he speaks about like,
all the cheese stays and then he kind of speaks about,
he kind of speaks about angels and power that the same time
I'm a much shorter.
of the isolation.
Yeah.
I mean, something that's interesting to me is that, you know, when it comes to times,
do you believe that it's like the mazo, the mazo was found in certain, certain, what
would they call them?
Would the Jews meet up to get the name started about that?
But, you know, they'll meet in places.
archaeologists they've found like,
from ancient like symbols of the
like that like all 12 zodiac signs like you believe that
part of God's plan of time. Would you think that's man made or
has Babylonian origin? What was what was the episode
father ended you remember the title where we talked about that
we talked about that the 12 tribes were associated with the 12
constellations it might have been we talked a lot about that.
Oh early on we were talking astrology I think maybe it might have been
And then...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, taught by a star to worship the son of righteousness. I think that's the one. That was one of our early episodes.
Yeah, yeah.
We get in a deep dive on that there.
Okay, then. So yeah, so what was the name of it again? Apologize taught by a star to worship the son of righteousness. It's one of our early episodes. I think within the first year.
Okay, that's that
so that I'm gonna check that out.
And I'm just real brief, brief comment.
I don't know, I don't wanna like dive into it,
but as far as the age, I was wondering
when it says like the punishment of an age
could refer to a time,
but far as the life of the age
could refer to the character of the age,
meaning that that life is incorruptible.
So like, there could be a certain nuance on
like on the contact of how it could still all meet.
right? But if those two things are paralleled in the text, right? You understand he
were parallelism and they're put one after the other saying that one has one new
on and the other one has an opposite nuance doesn't make a lot of sense. That's
what I was getting at. Yep. Okay. Okay. All right. Then we're pretty good. All right. Thank you.
Thank you, Antonio. Okay. We're gonna take one final call. No matter what
father Steven says. You can't call in the future. That's true.
you
I just meet another episode for this particular episode.
So okay, we have James.
James, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What's on your mind?
Are you in possession of a giant peach?
I don't have a giant peach, but I'm working on it.
Okay.
Oh, okay.
We're gonna figure it out.
So peach boars are real problem,
depending on some climates.
I just wanna put that out there.
So, not new ham sure.
Yeah, that's coming.
Can you grow peaches in New Hampshire?
Yeah, my grandfather grew peaches and pairs.
They did pretty well.
Oh, how about that?
You just gotta move to the country
and get yourself a lot of peaches.
Good, right?
That's what President's goal for in that one.
Okay, so James, what is on your mind?
So first I just wanna say that for many years,
I followed both of you, Father Andrew, Father Steven,
enjoyed the blog posts and the podcasts,
roads and nicks from a mares, etc.
Oh man, another deep magic.
Oh yeah.
Going way back, going way back.
And also as a recovering Calvinist, I have to say that there are Calvinists women out there.
They do exist.
We just got to go really looking.
You got to do a deep dive.
All right.
So what's your question for us tonight?
Yeah.
So my question was it's on topic, but it's definitely.
a little bit different than sort of what we've been talking about recently, which is there's
a sort of colloquial saying, at least in the English speaking world, that time heals all wounds.
And I was curious if there's an orthodox perspective on that concept of time heals all wounds
and what that might be and you know what you might have to say about that.
Yeah, well, it's really an ancient, it's an ancient sentiment.
actually. So as far as I can tell, the oldest instance of this is
Menander. So that's, you know, quote by St. Paul in first Corinthians.
There you go. Third, fourth century BC, where he says,
something like time is the healer of all necessary evils. And
there's a traster reference to, and Charlie Chris said there's a
there's a bit similar to that.
I mean,
Like the way that gets used right in popular culture now is essentially this idea of like just
weight and you'll feel better later. Right? Right. I mean, I think that's what most people
mean by it. But that by itself is not a Christian idea, you know, because sometimes you just feel
worse. I mean, people do, right? People are sometimes driven to despair or they don't repent of
there of whatever's going on.
you know, or things don't get better, right?
So it's not like it's just weighed and everything will be fine.
I actually, one of my favorite ways of favorite references
to dealing with this is from, oh, is it J Alfred Proofrock?
I don't remember the love song of J Alfred Proofrock
by T.S. Eliot, where he says something like time is no healer
for the patient is no longer...
there. I'm trying to remember which one that's wrong. But the point that he's making there is that
people change over time and so therefore the person who's healed is not the same person in a sense
as the person who was wounded. And so it's not time that did it. It's that the person was altered,
which I think in some ways is compatible with what we're saying. Right, it's not just about passage
of time. It's about the experience of the person. So I don't know, Father, you made reference to say
Paul Cordingman.
Ander is he does equal that bit. I'm blank. No, no, okay. Okay. I was like, wait a minute. No, that company grows good morals. Yes. Yes. Right.
Yeah.
But, Amanda was like a multi-time winner of the Athenian stage contests when the
Laurel like three or four years in a row.
Yeah.
I'm looking up that T.S.L.A. poem because I want to remember.
Oh, it's actually from the four quartets.
I can't believe that I didn't remember that.
How dare you, sir.
Try salvages.
I know four quartets is my favorite TSLA poetry.
It's ladies and gentlemen, it's probably the only poetry
by TSLA is relatively easy to understand
the first time you read it.
Yeah, I prefer the Hall of Men personally.
Oh, bitch, you do.
Anyway, yeah, James, I think that
Like the way it gets used now
is that it's kind of like I said, the sort of trite saying, you know, just wait and it'll
be fine. I mean, yeah, sure, like there's a certain psychological truth to that sometimes,
sometimes, like just chill out for a while. You'll feel better in the morning, sleep on it,
kind of thing. But I don't think a time by itself is a healer.
Yeah, I mean, especially for wounds infected.
Right.
Right, like if I'm a sinner and I don't change the intervene. Yeah, if I'm a sinner and I don't change
How is time going to help?
You know, could make things worse. Yeah, absolutely
Absolutely, so
But it's interesting. I mean, it's an interesting question and obviously
Various poets and theologians and playwrights and so forth have attempted to deal with it in one way or another
What is the relationship between time and
woundedness, time and healing, time and evil, you know, all that stuff. So it's a good question.
So thanks for calling and thanks for your support all these years.
Corey Bartlesons. Absolutely. Yes, I've Bartlesons and James.
Nice. I hadn't thought about that at the end of the long time.
So all right. The epic showdown between on the one hand Bartles and James and on the other
hand, seegrums, and...
Bruce Willis.
Ooh.
Tough car.
All right.
Well, it's the third half of the Laura Spirits podcast.
We'll talk about time.
One more.
No, okay, we don't have to.
It's Trudy.
She said it all down.
Oh, wow.
Did she just go home?
Like what?
No, she didn't go home.
But she's oh, she basically turned off.
She turned off the call center.
That's really.
Yeah.
Anyway.
Sorry, sorry.
I had no control.
People are excited about this stuff.
So I was not in command.
All right.
Let's say thank you to Santa Guston one more time.
Yes.
So Santa Guston.
Our friends say to Guston.
Isn't it nice how the nice things we've been saying
about Santa Guston tonight?
Even while picking on Calvinist and Plato,
somehow, we're managing to read nice to Santa Guston.
So this third half, what we're going to be talking about
talking about is
we're going to talk about. So we've talked about, we're going to be picking it up from
the first half. We talked about how time is really what we're talking about as humans.
What do we talk about time is the human experience of time, right? Not something that sort of
exists as a thing outside of us, right? And if you want to talk about the human experience
of time. There's only one place.
to go and it is St. Augustine. Folks may not know this, but books 10 and 11 of
St. Augustine's confessions. He deals with our experience of time, human
experience of time. And what he lays out there is it. It turns a human
understanding of this. When a hustle, probably the most famous,
modern phenomenologist. And if you don't believe that name me one that's more
famous. When he talks about time consciousness, he just crib St. Augustine. Like
it's a just puts into sort of modern German philosophical terms. What
St. Augustine said. Right. And Martin Heidegger...
Who again, I will point out favorite Nazi like if you got a pick one
Well, you don't want to pick one
But gun to your head you have to pick a favorite Nazi. It's got to be Martin Heidegger
That that's not controversial. Anyway
It's true. If you're honest with yourself. It's true for all of us
Martin Heidegger just picks up what hustle and hustle was kind of his mentor. So
Hi
begins existentialism, but he just when he's talking about being in time, he starts talking about time
consciousness, his whole idea of design. He's drawing very much on hustle, hustle, which means he's
just repeating St. Augustine. Right. And building on St. Augustine. So St. Augustine is the guy
for this. Right. He's the one who first really understood this. And nobody really has been able
to do much better since in the last 1600 years.
So, and what he's doing, even though the term phenomenology wasn't around yet,
Husserl was a phenomenologist, but St. Augustine is laying out the phenomenology of the human experience of time.
He's describing the way we as humans experience time.
And there are two main pieces to this. Right?
The first piece is memory. Right?
So...
So when we talk about our experience of time, our experience of time, we can frame as we
have an experience of there being a past.
Yeah.
We have an experience of there being a future.
And we have a kind of a loosive experience of there being a now.
But every time we say now that flies back into the past, right?
Like sort of into the face.
And then the folks whoops, I didn't live in that.
Now, now, now, yeah.
Yeah, I'm a little...
then. So we're going to kind of take that apart with St. Augustine here a little bit. So the
first part of that is memory, right? So we'll start with memory and we'll start with the past,
right? Because this is probably the least elusive of the three, right? Or at least we feel like it
is that we're talking about our experience, right? We feel like we know the past, we don't know the
the future.
President
it gets real slippery, right?
Then now gets real slippery.
So memory, right?
Memory obviously moves in one direction.
We don't remember the future.
We only remember the past, right?
Things slip into memory.
They come into our consciousness and then slip into memory.
As we go forward, already, the first two halves
of this program are memory hold for me.
I don't even know what I said.
And since we know you never listened to it,
you'll never know.
Bye.
We'll never know what happened.
So they slip into memory.
Now we tend to think about our memory
as if our sort of eyes and ears
were a camera and a microphone.
And our brain is sort of recording and storing
our experiences as they happen.
Yeah, which is not, no one's actually having that experience.
No, no, like if you think about something that happened like five minutes ago, you're not you can't even like replay it in your brain
Like it's not like a video. Yeah, that doesn't it doesn't work that way
But it's funny that we talk about it that way. I think maybe it's part of it. I think it's just because
That that's how the technology works and so
Right, we think we we analogize our brains to the technology that we've created right right
Yeah, or I should say I apologize our memories brain is not the right thing here
You know what I mean?
Yeah, well, I think before that it was pictures, right?
Like they would add to, oh, there I have pictures
in my head from the past, right?
When that was the technology, right?
But so the reality is what we're doing
when we remember something, right?
I'm about to say a bunch of things
that all of the married people listening
will instantly identify with.
When we remember some
thing, only about 10% of it is made up of actual sense memories. A mixture of images,
sounds, smells, tastes, feelings, right, about 10% of it is that. The other 90% we reconstruct
with our imagination.
Yeah, I mean, you could say that it's just slipping into the
future.
So we do this reconstruction, right?
And if we do the same reconstruction over and over and over again.
So something happens to me, I tell, I decide it's a funny story.
I tell the funny story to 23 different people, you know,
every three or four months, I meet somebody who hasn't heard it
and I tell them the story, right?
that that story is going to get kind of cemented in my
brain, just from telling and retelling and retelling and retelling it. I'm essentially
going to memorize the retelling, right? Yeah. And that's going to reinforce to me that
that thing that I retold in all its details is what actually happened. Right. I mean,
that becomes the story, you know, that becomes the I've had the time of my life. I've never
felt this way. I actually have felt this way before quite often when you're doing the
that jokes.
It's been a while since I actually just had a bunch of jokes lined up to throw out at you just for the moment to use it.
And you waited until now, right?
Like, you know, I don't know the episodes almost over. I gotta get these in.
Um,
Sunbife.
Anyway, right.
And so what I meant by our married audience members, right, is that sometimes you and another person close to you
Well, share an experience and you'll both sort of...
recreate your memories of it, and they will conflict in certain regards.
Yeah, yeah.
If you want to just, you know, scuttle your intimacy, say this magical phrase, that's
not what I said.
Yeah.
It magically works.
It's amazing.
And each of you will be utterly convinced that the way you remember it is what really
happened.
Yeah.
And you can't you can't escape that.
And neither of you are lying.
Right. You know, you'll each assist the other one is falsifying.
This is your full memory.
You honestly have recreated it differently because you had 10% to work from
and it was a different 10% by the way, each of you.
The rest of it has been put together by imagination, but you'll be utterly convinced.
Right.
that you did it and
And you are right.
And that's sort of on a micro level of sort of individual memories of individual events, right, where we experience it that way.
But we also on sort of a more macro level, right.
We will have sort of a big overall story that we tell ourselves that's connected to the idea of our identity next episode next week.
we're going to talk more about identity.
That's sort of my story overall how I got here to where I am today, right?
And that is going to be a very selective reading, chaining together of those memories.
Right? I'm not going to remember everything.
And if you asked me ten years ago to tell you my story,
I would have chained together a group of memories to do that.
If you ask me today, it might be a very different
story. There might be memories that would have been part of my story that I
thought were significant 10 years ago that now don't seem that significant to me.
Yeah and sometimes you like retrieve stuff from before like you like wait a
second. This actually makes all this other stuff make more sense and then that
gets incorporated into into the story. Right. Right. But that again is this
selective recreation and imagine putting together of this story. Yeah. Right. And
And...
Again, this is I'm not talking about false, I'm not talking about lying.
I'm not talking about making anything up, right?
But this happens a level of our experience from our perspective of remembering.
We are just remembering.
Yeah.
And we're not consciously choosing like, oh, this is really important.
And though, oh, that isn't.
So I'm going to forget that and remember this, right?
It just is happening, right?
Naturally in our experience.
So our past is kind of amorphous.
It's way more amorphous.
It's not a recording.
Yeah.
right? It's way more selective in terms of the story.
You can't save time in a ball.
You just have to.
But if you could, you'd save it up.
That's right. And spend it with hopefully someone other than me like your
wife. Yeah, I wouldn't pick you.
Just get that on the table right now. That would be like super awkward.
But even though at this point, anytime you go somewhere,
I'm not everybody just asking where I am.
Because people don't know this, but Father Edward, I normally, most of our lives, we spend
riding around town on a bicycle built for two.
So I understand you're confusion when you see only one of us.
Your wheel is way bigger.
I should, everyone needs to know that your wheel is way bigger.
Yeah, it's one of those old bikes with the giant wheel and then the little wheel.
That's right.
So...
And we talked about we mentioned when we were sort of teasing this episode, the fact that
another thing that affects our view of the past is actually affects our view of the
flow of time.
That when we have new experiences and more experiences, those make more memories.
And so time seems to move more slowly when we have more memories based on more
experiences and it seems to move more quickly when we're having fewer experiences and generating
fewer memories.
Right.
And we've all sort of experienced this.
In the sense that, you know, when you've got a few weeks where basically you just go through
your routine every day, right, the time seems to kind of fly by because, you know, there's
nothing super memorable going on on any given day.
as other times.
in your life where lots of things happen, you know, a week might seem like a long time
because of all the things that are happening.
Yeah.
Right?
During that period, right?
Again, as we said before, time always moves at one second per second, right?
But really when we're talking about time, we're talking about our experience of it.
And the rate of passage of time, especially when we're talking about the past here, shifts
a lot in our experience.
based on these different variables.
So that's one side.
If we're talking about it again, how St. Augusta talks about this.
On the one hand, we've got memory.
Then on the other side, we've got anticipation, which
is directed toward the future.
When St. Augusta talks about this, the biggest
made example he uses is music.
And I'm darn near tone deaf.
So that's
why I'm not using his analogy.
Don't read the confessions.
I remember, obviously, I'm not gonna throw you
under the bus here because I know you don't have any feelings.
So I remember, I remember,
because boys and girls, you may not know
that Father Stephen, I once, for a few weeks,
we shared the same job.
I was outgoing, he was incoming,
being the assistant pastor of particular church.
That's why we bought the bicycle.
That's right.
And I remember...
I used to remember one of the questions I was submitted to be answered in the bulletin
like right after your showtup was, you know, is it required?
Is it required?
Something like, is it included in pre-straining that they learn how to sink?
I was submitted right after your showtup.
I was like, oh, day.
See, folks at home, like, it's gotten better.
Why would someone be insulted by that?
Right.
Right, well...
I mean, I have an ego, but it's not a stupid ego.
Like, I know I can't sing, right?
Like, I'm aware.
Like, you're not telling me anything I don't already know,
but let me reassure people
if you ever do come to visit our parish.
I have worked very hard in the 15 intervening years
and I'm now mediocre.
There you go.
So through applying myself, I've become,
Hmm.
Ah, that's ringin'.
Yeah.
You didn't even see the really bad days.
Like when I first became a subdeacon.
Right.
I still remember after I've been a subdeacon for like four or five months doing like the
little litneys and the liturgy.
Yeah.
Mostly nothing.
Kind of a weird and yogi thing.
Yeah.
For a hot minute there of that era.
and I was first doing the litigings, I still remember it.
I was like three months in to doing these every liturgy and the choir director came up to be like super excited at the end of liturgy
It was like I was actually able to take a pitch off of you today. Oh, man. Yes. That's love
So that was you right like I had I had spent a couple of years refining my craft already by the time you experienced that
So that tells you how bad it was before
And it's a hereditary thing
thing.
My grandfather was thrown out of a Dutch reformed church choir, asked to leave because he couldn't sing.
And my father was told to just mouth it.
Nice in the choir.
So this is a proud family tradition.
Wow.
And we will continue with the episode. Don't worry people, but I do have to do one more point.
Part of my dad's reaction, right? So when I was coming into the Orthodox church,
my
my dad attended his first Orthodox liturgy and being Dutch and blunt he said to me
so you're half decent at preaching and you can't sing so you go and join a church where they
preach for five minutes and sing everything. May God rest his magnificent soul and I was like
fair.
Like a fair point.
Nice.
Yeah.
But so you see yeah, we don't usually do big digressions of the third half.
Yes, but all this by way of this is why I'm not using the same analogy that St. Augustine does because to be honest, I don't understand the whole musical thing.
Yes.
That's, so we've talked about memory.
The other side is anticipation.
Anticipation of the future,
like memory, anticipation also involves imagination, right?
Because what we're doing with anticipation is where
imagining possible futures. Yeah. Right. And that could be anticipation is a more
positive word for it. Like we're anticipating something in the future. You know, it could
also be dread of what could happen in the future. Right. Exile. Right.
Existential dread. Right. The ultimately, right. If we're going to talk about Heidegger,
right? The fact that we realized that at some point we're going to die in the future.
That is looming in front of us.
But so we have this direction toward the future where we're imagining these potential futures
that either looking at them with anticipation or some level of dread.
Right?
So we remember the past, if these memories of the past, we have this anticipation of the
future.
And in between, there is this sort of tension between the two.
And that tension between the two is what we call now or any given moment.
which is constantly moving, constantly sliding back into the past.
Yeah. Right.
And so it's just this tension. Right.
It's not a thing you could ever put your finger on,
because it's always sliding away. Right.
This is why, so sometimes, when you hear people talk about God's relationship with time,
They will talk about, well, God's outside of time, or God isn't...
subject to categories, to temporal categories. And so that means that God is in an eternal
present, right? But that doesn't really make sense if we understand what we mean by the
present, right? Because God doesn't have like memories of the past and anticipation of
the future and this tension between the two. He's not living in this constant tension.
The way we are between, right? To talk about the present kind of requires that there
or be this-
framing of future and rest. Right. Right. So that doesn't really make sense. I know
what people try to get at when they say that, but it doesn't really make sense. Right. But
it's yet another attempt to try to describe God's relationship to time in terms of our human
relationship with time. Right. Well, it's just like always now for him. Well, what would
that mean? Right. Now, this is the part that we promised you. We would return to our
Jesus Christ.
Christ, when we were in the first half.
Yeah.
We had a bunch of people in the chat on the YouTube's, ask this question, like, well, wait,
Jesus is human, didn't he experience time?
Right.
You know, here we go.
That's probably about to be fulfilled.
We are coming back to this, right?
So we talked about, we raised those questions in the first half about, you know, how Christ
then relates to time.
And so...
So this present as tension between anticipation and memory, this experience, this human experience,
is one to which Christ voluntarily subjected himself.
What do you mean by that?
We've talked about this before.
voluntarily took upon himself the sinless passions related to human.
Yeah, like getting tired or hungry or thirsty. We know that we know that are not sinful. Yeah, yeah, we know that not because
We know what it's like to be Jesus Christ
But rather because he said things like I thirst right or I am weary
So Christ voluntarily subjected himself these things so Christ in his humanity had experiences
He was acted upon because he
allowed himself to be acted upon voluntarily. Right? You took about himself hunger, thirst,
tiredness, weakness, right? You took these things on himself. And one of the things he took on
himself was this tension of the present, of this experience of time. And we can see this,
right? We can see this because for example, in the Garden of Gethsemane,
Right, we see Christ's humanity.
expressed in his human will expressed in the dread with which he looks at his coming death.
So that shows us that this is something to which Christ voluntarily subjected himself.
Yeah, and I'm also thinking about the other references in the Gospels, where he talks about his hour.
right? This is not this is not my hour my hour.
is now come, you know, that kind of stuff. Right. And so this is a voluntary, just like he voluntarily
was incarnate and therefore was occupying a physical space, even though that doesn't mean he wasn't
everywhere else, by the way, yeah. Being God. Right. When Christ is incarnate, he does not give up
being God in any respect. Right. He adds being human.
right? He adds human nature. He does not subtract anything from his divinity. But so he
voluntarily subjects us all those things. And that doesn't mean that God the Father or the Holy
Spirit are subjected to those things. Right? The fact that Christ submitted to this tension of
the present. Does it mean that God the Father or the Holy Spirit are subject to it any
more than God the Father or the Holy Spirit get hungry or thirsty or tired or sweat.
Right? Grise voluntarily submitted to those things up to and including dying.
So there's the answer to that.
Right.
So the kind of, the kind of put a file.
point on this, pun kind of intent. We've talked in several previous episodes about the news, and I
know those were all totally clear and easy, so this will now simplify this whole complex episode for
you. But basically what we came to is the idea that our news are mined, right, where we're talking
about it in a spiritual sense, is a sort of point of attention, right, where we can turn our attention,
the eye of our mind to something, right? We can focus it on something.
Right? And the way this relates to our experience of time is that we can direct the focus of our attention to the past.
Right? And often that we could do that in bad ways. Right? In the sense that we can think about our past in ways that bring us guilt, shame, despair. Right?
even over, you know.
since that have been confessed and forgiven and repented of, right? Or losses we've suffered.
We can focus our attention on the past on things that have happened to us and drive from that bitterness and resentment and anger, right?
And let that faster. We can also, on the other hand, direct that point of attention and our focus to the future, right?
to that anticipation or that dread.
Right?
And we can get all kinds of anxiety and worry and concern about these imagined futures that
present themselves to us, right?
And we can have all kinds of thoughts coming into our head trying to pull us toward the
past or toward the future to worry or to be angry or to despise it in all these different
directions.
or we can direct our focus to that point of tension of this
present moment, right? In the sense that by directing our attention to it, that then makes us free
to act in it, right? And so that's an important relationship, not just our experience, but how we can
then reflect and focus on that experience, right? And how that can work for good or, or bad.
So next time, which is next week on Thursday.
We're going to move from this. We're going to talk about identity. We're going to talk about the body.
We're going to talk about bodily resurrection and we're going to talk about the life of the world to come
based on some of the things that we talked about now tonight.
And hopefully, understand a little and hopefully, that second half, if things are still a little
murky or difficult and stuff, hopefully that second half of the package will help clarify
everything and bring everything together.
Amen.
So as I've been pondering exactly what to say at the end of this episode, there's
There's a couple things that come to mind for me
My big takeaways
One and I said this earlier, but I wanted to maybe expand on it a little bit is that
It's important especially to understand that God is not bound by anything at all
including time and
And...
I think we tend to believe that God is bound because we're bound.
We don't know what it's like not to be subject to time.
So we just tend to think that God is subject to time because that's our experience of it,
so therefore must be, you know.
And so to me, one of the important things about one of the reasons why having this discussion
is important is because it underlines that God is really, really, really is not bound by.
by time, by anything at all, but in this case by time. And if you assume he's bound by time,
that creates all kinds of theological problems, not just in terms of theology, how we're saved,
in terms of who God himself is. And we've talked about a bunch of those problems that come as
as a result of that.
And there is actually a spiritual posture issue
in the midst of this, which is...
humility, humility. The reason why there is this tradition of apophatic theology in the Orthodox
tradition is not because it's cool to say things like if God is love, God is not love. If God is
present, he is not present. You know like it's not because it's cool to say those things or you know
sounds weird and mystical and Eastern or whatever, but it's really about humility. It's about knowing
that, no matter what I say about God.
But it's not enough.
And it doesn't begin to cover it.
It doesn't mean that we can't say anything because God has revealed himself.
We can say what's been revealed.
And we can reflect upon that revelation.
That's what theology is.
We can proclaim the things He told us to proclaim.
But humility is to not take our speculations and assumptions and put them on God.
part of the reason for this apophatic...
to say it's not this, it's not this, it's not this, it's not this, is exactly to exercise humility.
And it's not that we should exercise humility because that's the smart thing to do as an intellectual person or whatever.
It's that humility is the path of salvation.
It's not possible to be saved without humility.
It's required.
And we're able to be humble by joining ourselves to Christ who humbled himself even to death, as the scriptures tell us.
So there is actually a practical reason to engage with theology in this way, not just because
it's right, but because it's actually good for us, right?
And so then that kind of leads me to the second thing I wanted to focus on here at the end,
which is that as we engage with time ourselves in this age, the age that we're in now, the
page that...
and anybody listening to us is currently in,
that a healthy relationship with time
is to always ask the question
and live according to the answer to this question
of how can I use this for repentance?
So if I do focus my attention on something in the past,
I could, as Father Stephen said,
focus
on things that are going to darken my news, darken it because I'm focusing on evil.
Maybe it's, as he said, sins that I have already confessed and repented of by return,
return to them.
It could be resentments I have.
I'm holding on being unforgiving, right?
are some possibilities. I could also have it, you know, towards the future.
and focus it on fear and lack of trust in God,
all that sort of stuff.
And certainly in the present, as well,
there's all kinds of dark ways
to have a relationship to time.
But if I look at the things that have happened in my past,
the memories that I have,
and I see how God is leading me to salvation,
I see the gifts that God has given.
Like there's a very practical thing
that says in scripture, and everything give thanks.
I mean, I have to be, say, I'm really happy
that it doesn't see in everything.
you thankful. Everything give thanks. Everything give thanks. Right. And you know, the posture
towards the future is a posture of hope. Of hope. There's a lot of posture of despair in our time
and of fear. Right. And connected with the past of resentment. A lot of this is going on.
And I think that the twin virtues of gratitude and hope
If we really embrace them and really practice them, practice them, no one's asking you
to feel anything, to practice them, right?
That's going to be transformative.
And I don't just mean this in some kind of like ethereal, theoretical way, right?
attitude and hope that works in your marriage.
That works in your parenting.
That works in your friendships.
That works in your job.
That works with your fellow students.
That works with your fellow parishioners.
That works in your relationship with your father, confessor.
That works in the way that you interact with the world at large.
Gratitude and hope.
And...
If we do live in gratitude and hope, give thanks,
and everything give thanks,
and always be looking to the hope of salvation from Christ,
then not only will we be able to walk through this world
in a lighter, more peaceful, more joyful way,
but we will be a light to those around us.
We will be a light to those around us.
Not all overexp-
Experiences are the same.
Not everybody's having the same experience
of the difficulties of the world, for sure.
I mean, a lot of our lives are easier than others.
A lot of our lives are more difficult than others.
But we all have that possibility of gratitude and hope.
We can do those things, right?
So that's what I want us to walk away with.
It's definitely what I want for me
and it's what I want for all of y'all as well.
Right.
So Steven saw yours.
All y'all, you went wild.
That's the pervasive plural.
Yeah.
Somewhat relatedly.
Where are we ended off there?
Talking about our focus being on the past or the future.
Is we're all painfully aware?
aware because most of us have things that we might consider changing
You can't change the past.
For the most part you can't even voluntarily change your memories of the past.
And that's one of the sort of devils in getting focused on the past.
you're getting focused on a bunch of things that you can't change in the past.
Like we talked about last episode, sorry Kenneth Copeland and sorry Oprah, you can't just
will the future you want into existence by wanting it or speaking it or whatever and
visioning it.
And so when we put our focus on the future and on all those imagined futures, we end up
with the worry with the anxiety, but we can't affect the future we want in the future.
We can't do anything in the future.
But if we focus on that tension between the two, that present moment in which we are, that
is the place where we can do things that affect the past.
It won't change the past in the sense of making it not have happened anymore, right, like
going into a time machine and hitting ourselves over the head.
Right. But for example, that moment of the present is where we can repent of our
sins. That moment of the present is where we can try to fix some of the
things we've broken, try to heal some of the people we've hurt and some of the
wounds we've inflicted on ourselves. That can happen in the present. And while we
We can't in the present name or declare or envision or vision border.
whatever and make the future we want manifest itself. We can actually do things in the present
that will help bring about the future that we want. We can take actions that will make our lives
in our world's better places. Part of repentance is not just oriented toward the past, it's also
oriented toward the future, toward not making the same
mistakes and toward doing good in place of the bad and the evil that we've done in the past.
But I want to go even a step further than that in terms of the present being the place where we can act to heal the past, to prepare the past, or pen to the past, and to build the better future.
and directly connect this to our prayer.
to our life of prayer. A lot of our prayer, I think, if people are like me at all, is
related to either the past or the future. Either we're praying about things that
happen in the past, sort of repentantly, right? Or we're praying about things in the
future. Asking God for things, asking Him to protect us from things that
We're worried about in the future, trying to help all
ourselves trust him in going into the future. But not much
of our prayers aimed at the present. Not much of our prayer, I
think is aimed at asking God to give me the wisdom now I
need to do the things now that I need to do. Right?
Asking God to show me the things now.
the opportunities now that I need to not miss because I'm focused on my past or my imagined future.
Right?
Asking God to connect us to the people, show us the people, lead us to the people now that we need to connect with, to lead us to the place we need to be.
Right now, not someday.
Right? And not just a cycle of remorse about the past, but helping lead in guidance to do those
things now. Right? That we need to do, to empower us to do them, to strengthen us, to do them, to show
them to us. Right? Because if we continue to wander through our lives looking backwards or looking
far off into the distance, we're going to keep running into things.
Sometimes the same
things over and over again. And we're going to miss a whole lot of things that were important.
That were important, not just in the moment that they're important, but are important in reference to
the things that are passed and the things in our future that we're so concerned with.
Right. We're so concerned about the problem that we miss the solution. So concerned about the disease,
Please remiss the care.
Right? Because our focus is wrong. Our focus is wrong. So I think it's important that our
prayer life reflect the fact that we have this slippery tension of now in which to act.
always slipping away. Now we need God's help to act in it in the way.
that he wants us to act to participate in what he's doing in that moment. Not what he wants to do,
but needs our help to do, but what he's actually doing. To find it, to get on board with it, to
participate in it, and to be transformed by it. We can't restructure our past. If we want to
restructure our future, we have to restructure our now. We have to get to work and we have
to do it. And so I think that's one of the most important takeaways we can have in terms
of our relationship with time is our relationship with that ever-slipery present moment.
Amen. Well, that's our show for tonight, everyone. Thank you all for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live, you can still contact us. You can email us
at LordofSpiritsinHitFate.com. You can send a message to our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish,
head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Sometimes you picture me, I'm walking too far ahead.
You're calling to me.
I can't hear what you've said.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page, join our discussion group,
reviews and ratings where they go.
and share the show with a friend.
And probably be sure to go to www.hpfa.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Then you say, go slow and I fall behind.
The second hand on one.
Thank you.
Good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the l-
of spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom and strength and honor.
and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.